<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An examination of Dr. Comber's Scholastical history of the primitive and general use of liturgies in the Christian church by S.B.</title>
            <author>Bold, S. (Samuel), 1649-1737.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28584</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3479</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18212</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12212258</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12212258</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56330</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28584)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56330)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 127:12-13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An examination of Dr. Comber's Scholastical history of the primitive and general use of liturgies in the Christian church by S.B.</title>
                  <author>Bold, S. (Samuel), 1649-1737.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to S. Bold. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [9].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library and British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Comber, Thomas, 1645-1699. --  Scholastical history of the primitive and general use of liturgies.</term>
               <term>Liturgies, Early Christian.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56330:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56330:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EXAMINATION OF Dr. <hi>COMBER</hi>'s SCHOLASTICAL HISTORY OF THE Primitive and General Uſe OF LITURGIES IN THE <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi> By <hi>S. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> eſt quodcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pietatis officium, etiamſi à privato praeſtetur. <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſ. Caſaub. exercit. in Baron. xvi. p. 383.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Nemo autem verſatus in Graecorum Patrum lectione, ignorat, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> perſaepe illis dici quicquid fit ad Deum colendum. <bibl>
                  <hi>Id. p. 384.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens Head Ally</hi> in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter Row.</hi> MDCXC.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:56330:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56330:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE following Papers were writ ſome months ſince, and if the Author had known they would have been publiſhed at this time, I do not doubt but they would have been accompanied with the like account of what Doctor <hi>Comber</hi> hath produced for <hi>Liturgies</hi> in the Fourth <hi>Century.</hi> The Author is not one who is wedded to a <hi>Party;</hi> He hath often ſaid, he knows not any one Party of a <hi>particular De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomination,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:56330:3"/> but it hath ſome things which either do, or by reaſon of an alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of circumſtances, may deſerve to be <hi>rectified.</hi> He thinks what is really good and commendable in every Party ſhould be <hi>approved:</hi> And he wiſhes that what is not ſo, in every Party, might be univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally underſtood, and laid aſide, or amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He is a <hi>Conformiſt,</hi> upon Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples he thinks he can juſtifie, but which are more <hi>comprehenſive</hi> than thoſe which ſome appear to be influenced by in their <hi>Conformity.</hi> He uſeth the <hi>Liturgy of the Church of England in his</hi> Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating in the Publick Worſhip, as fully as the <hi>Law</hi> requires. And he is ſo far from condemning the Publick Worſhip of <hi>Pious and Judicious Proteſtants</hi> who do not tye up themſelves to <hi>Preſcribed Forms,</hi> that he joins with them in their <hi>Publick Worſhip,</hi> as he hath opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. He is troubled to ſee ſo great an <hi>averſion</hi> to a General <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants in this Land, and that old <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities</hi> are awakened out of their <hi>late Slumber.</hi> He is of opinion that the
<pb facs="tcp:56330:3"/> 
               <hi>Church of England</hi> is much prejudiced by the <hi>Indiſcretions</hi> of many who pretend an <hi>extraordinary Zeal</hi> for <hi>Her.</hi> The matters we differ about are very ſeldom rightly <hi>Stated.</hi> Arguments are not well adjuſted to what is in debate. What is offered for proof, is too ordinarily put upon the <hi>Rack,</hi> and by overſtraining it, it ſerves only for a <hi>Pompous Show,</hi> and is of no real uſe at all. Though Doctor <hi>Comber</hi> hath often expreſſed himſelf in ſuch a manner, as would juſtifie ſome <hi>keen Reflections,</hi> yet this Author hath forborn them, becauſe he would not willingly <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate</hi> any man of <hi>Learning</hi> or <hi>Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity.</hi> And therefore he hath mainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined himſelf to a fair Repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Doctor's Authorities,</hi> which he hopes can yield no offence to any man of a ſober and honeſt mind.</p>
            <p>The Author of the following Papers doth think, that to do. <hi>Liturgies</hi> right in a full Diſcourſe (eſpecially Hiſtory) of that matter, ſome notice ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the various uſe of the word <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian Church,</hi> and of the
<pb facs="tcp:56330:4"/> time when it was firſt uſed with that ſtrictneſs of ſignification, Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> hath aſſigned it, in his ſtating the point. For he ſaith, It was at firſt of a very general importance, and was not limited to <hi>Publick Offices.</hi> That when it came to be uſed in a more <hi>appropriate</hi> ſenſe, it was applied particularly to every <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Office.</hi> And that after it was in a ſpecial manner appropriated to <hi>Forms of Prayer,</hi> it had not for a long time, that ſtrictneſs of ſignification it has in Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi>'s ſtating the matter. And he further conceives, that this is not the proper ſignification of a <hi>Liturgy</hi> as uſed and enjoined in the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Therefore he thinks, that inſtead of endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to prove the <hi>Antiquity</hi> of <hi>Liturgies</hi> in that ſenſe, we ſhould rather endeavour to rectifie the <hi>miſtake</hi> which hath unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ariſen concerning a <hi>Liturgy,</hi> as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned and uſed in our <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having given you this account of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r, and his deſign in the following Papers, I leave you to peruſe the Papers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to judge as you ſhall ſee ſit, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:56330:4"/> the Doctor have produced ſubſtantial Proof, that Liturgies, or Preſcribed Forms of Prayer, were only, and unvariably uſed in the Chriſtian Church during the Three Firſt Centuries.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:56330:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>P 2. l. <hi>ult.</hi> r. <hi>preſcribed.</hi> p. 4. l. 29. for <hi>truly,</hi> r. <hi>freely.</hi> p. 6. l. 22. after <hi>out,</hi> r. <hi>of.</hi> p. 16. marg. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. p. 18. l. 11. r. <hi>Lucian.</hi> p. 29. l. 9. for <hi>truth,</hi> r. <hi>proof.</hi> p. 36. l. 6. dele <hi>as.</hi> p. 37. l. 29. after <hi>ſubject,</hi> r. <hi>matter.</hi> p. 38. l. 11. after <hi>any,</hi> r. <hi>other.</hi> p. 40. l. 26. r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56330:5"/>
            <head>AN EXAMINATION OF Dr. <hi>COMBERS</hi> Teſtimonies FOR LITURGIES (During the three Firſt Centuries) <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ABOUT the middle of the laſt month, I received, by your order, <q rend="inline">Dr. <hi>Combers</hi> Scholaſtical Hiſtory of the Primitive and General uſe of Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church, together with an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>David Clarkſon</hi>'s late Diſcourſe concerning Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies.</q> I now return you my thanks for it; and I would have done it ſooner, but that ſome buſineſſes call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me from home immediately after I received it, even before I had time to peruſe it. I now certifie you that I have read it: And I do herewith ſend you what I take to be a true account of the meaning of thoſe Teſtimonies the Doctor doth alledge in the three firſt <hi>Centurys,</hi> for Liturgies. I forbear many Reflections, which ſeveral paſſages in the Doctor's Book would give
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56330:6"/> abundant occaſion for. My deſign is little more than juſt to preſent you with the Doctor's quotations in their plain and entire ſenſe. Your opinion of the Doctor's performance, I perſwade my ſelf, is not ſuch, as will prejudice you againſt evidence. I therefore leave you to judge, whether his Authorities be to his purpoſe, and whether his Inferences be ſo <hi>rational</hi> as he pretends his Hiſtory is <hi>Scholaſtical;</hi> and whether his Book may properly be ſaid to contain an Anſwer to Mr <hi>Clarkſon</hi>'s Diſcourſe of Liturgies.</p>
            <p>You will make the eaſier and more juſt determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if the matter be firſt a little ſtated: for then you will perceive what the Doctor ſhould prove; And whether what he offers for proof, do reach the point he hath undertaken to diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Therefore you muſt be ſure to remember, that Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> is far enough from aſſerting, that Forms of Prayer are intrinſically evil.<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">He does not deny but there were ſome Forms of Prayer of old, <hi>viz.</hi> Arbitrary and particular, ſuch as this or that perſon compoſed himſelf, or made choice of, compoſed by others,<note place="margin">P. 3.</note> for his uſe in publick. He owns the Lords Prayer was uſed anciently, tho far otherwiſe than of late.<note place="margin">P. 4.</note> He grants that divers Churches had a certain order, wherein they agreed to adminiſter the ſeveral parts of worſhip, and particularly the ſeverals in the Sacraments, ſo as each had its known and fixed place. That this order was ſetled in ſome Churches by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, and in ſome there was in time a Rule for it. He ſaith there was alſo ſome kind of uniformity in their Sacramental Prayers,<note place="margin">P. 5.</note> that is, a general agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to pray for the ſame things,<note place="margin">Idem.</note> tho not in the ſame words.</q>
            </p>
            <p>He expreſly relates what it is, which is the point in diſpute.<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> And declares <q rend="inline">That by preſcribing Forms
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56330:6"/> are meant, ſuch as are impoſed upon the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, ſo as thoſe muſt be uſed, and no other, nor otherwiſe, without adding, detracting, or tranſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. This (ſaith Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi>) is it which is deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.<note place="margin">P. 6.</note> That in the Ancient Church, for many ages after Chriſt, ſuch Liturgies and Forms of Prayer were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly impoſed on thoſe who adminiſtred the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as are before deſcribed.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee what was denied, as well as what was granted by Mr <hi>Clarkson,</hi> and therefore what the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor was to prove. If the Doctor's quotations be not home to this point, they do not reach that for which he doth pretend to produce them. And whether for the firſt three <hi>Centuries</hi> his Authorities do amount to a proof of what is in diſpute; yea or ſo much as of Forms of Prayer, you may conclude as you ſhall ſee fit, when you have conſidered the following account of them.</p>
            <p>Before I enquire into the paſſages the Doctor doth quote for the proof of Liturgies in the particular <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies,</hi> as they come in their order, I will take notice of a few paſſages which occur in his <hi>Diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Grounds for Liturgies in Holy Scripture,</hi> which takes up ſome Pages, before he makes his entrance on the Firſt <hi>Century.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">The Doctor ſaith the Holy Bible makes it appear,<note place="margin">P. 2.</note> that the People of God, from the beginning, did ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally uſe Forms of Prayer and Praiſes in their Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip.</q> Now ſuppoſing this to be true, to make it reach the preſent purpoſe, he ſhould prove they did not, nor might not uſe any Prayers or Praiſes, but thoſe very Forms;<note place="margin">Idem.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">Yea (ſaith the Doctor) God preſcribes a Form of Prayer for the penitent <hi>Jews,</hi> and charges them to take words with them, and turn to the Lord and ſay, <hi>Take away all Iniquity,</hi> &amp;c.</q> Hoſ.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56330:7"/> 14.2, 3, 4. 'Tis true, God doth command them to uſe words in their Prayers, and directs them what ſort of words to uſe; but let the Doctor anſwer when he thinks fit, whether God doth bind them to uſe no words but what are there mentioned? <q rend="inline">But further, Forms of Prayer and Praiſe were indited by the Spirit of God for the publick ſervice of the Temple, and commanded by the Lord to be uſed there.</q> Is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference from hence plain and juſt; Therefore men may deviſe Prayers of their own, and oblige the Church to uſe theſe, and none but theſe.</p>
            <p>The Doctor refers to Doctor <hi>Hammond</hi> and Doctor <hi>Lightfoot,</hi> for proof that the Jews had a fixed Liturgy; whether their proof be ſolid touching that matter, would be too great a diverſion to inquire. But if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion required, I ſhould not be afraid to undertake to produce the Authorities thoſe two Learned Doctors build their proof, upon, for ſome things, the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will not allow we muſt acquieſce in upon their teſtimony.</p>
            <p>I will not inſiſt on the difference betwixt the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and Chriſtian Church-State. For we may ſuppoſe, Forms might be of general uſe among the Jews, and yet there be no neceſſity of an expreſs abrogation of that way, to warrant peoples addreſſing themſelves publickly to God in another way than by ſtinted Forms. For Prayer being commanded, and there being two ways wherein this duty might be performed, <hi>viz.</hi> by ſtinted Forms, and by expreſſing themſelves truly, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to general Occaſions, and particular Emergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies. There appears not any neceſſity that the uſe of Forms, as to the Lawfulneſs thereof, muſt of neceſſity be abrogated, in order to it's being Lawful to uſe the other way.<note place="margin">P. 5, 6.</note> But if we would proſecute the Doctors way of Arguing on this occaſion, aright, ſomthing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56330:7"/> elſe will follow than what the Doctor doth conclude, even what the Doctor, I am perſwaded, would not be very willing to ſtand to. <q rend="inline">For ſeeing the Jews did worſhip God acceptably, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by ſet Forms, and Chriſt and his Apoſtles did joyn in theſe Forms, and never reprove the Jews for uſing them.</q> The moſt obvious inference will be, That Chriſtians muſt now uſe thoſe very Forms, and none but them, unleſs thoſe Forms be abrogated, and a poſitive inſtitution of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Forms be left upon Record, either in the Goſpels, or Epiſtles. For by the Doctors diſcourſe, the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples had Forms of Prayers, which muſt certainly be Jewiſh Forms, and Chriſt only taught them another Form, which they were to add to thoſe they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; yea, according to what the Doctor relates, the Lord Jeſus, when he provided his Diſciples a New Form to be added to the reſt, was not only ſo far from diſcharging people, and ſetting his Diſciples free from the ſtinted way of Liturgies, but from their obligation to the Jewiſh Forms, <q rend="inline">That he would conſine himſelf in the very Prayer he made them (whereby they were to be known from all others, to be his Diſciples) to the Jewiſh Liturgy; ſo that there ſhould not be one ſentence in his Prayer, but what he took out of the Jewiſh Prayers then in uſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now thoſe who devote themſelves to ſuch notions as theſe, may do well to conſider, whether if it be ſo (as the Doctor reportes) that Chriſt took every ſentence of his Prayer out of the Jewiſh Prayers, and taught it his Diſciples, that they might add it to their other Forms (which were Jewiſh) the obligation to uſe this as a Form of Prayer, and to uſe thoſe other Forms, to which they were to add it, be not of equal durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? But alas! whether will ſome mens pretences to reading hurry them? What work will be made of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56330:8"/> if the forced conceptions of ſome men who would be thought to have read much muſt be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? Some do repreſent matters in ſuch a manner, as if they had a mind to perſwade people, that the Lord Jeſus was anointed with the Spirit, only to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the meanneſs of his education, not to inable him to form and compoſe a Prayer himſelf, but only to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and cull ſentences out of other peoples Prayers, and then put them together into one form. Not many years ago other matters were repreſented at ſuch a rate, by another hand, as if the Spirit had been given to the Apoſtles to furniſh them immediately (becauſe they had not been bred to ſuch matters) with Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical notions, and ſome critical niceties, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly was given to St. <hi>John</hi> to inable him to write his Epiſtle in a Platonick ſtrain. How far this ſort of deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may ſerve a particular intereſt for a while, I will not inquire. But it hath no probable tendency to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the main deſign of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="inline">The Doctor ſaith that Chriſt in giving his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples a new Form (when they deſired him to teach them to pray) and Coppying the ſeveral Petitions out the Jewiſh Liturgy,<note place="margin">P. 6.</note> inſtead of intimating that he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to reform the old method of praying by Forms, did ſhew his approbation of praying to God in a preſcribed Form.</q> But he might with as much clearneſs have puſht his inference from thoſe premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes further, <hi>viz.</hi> That he did ſhew his approbation (at leaſt) of his Followers compoſing Forms of Prayer (if they are to compoſe any for conſtant pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick uſe) only out of the Jewiſh Liturgies. I may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind you that the Doctor doth ordinarily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe too looſely concerning Forms of Prayer, as not being mindful of what he hath undertaken to diſcourſe of. For if he find any words uſed in Prayer, which
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56330:8"/> were to be met with any where elſe before, thoſe words he alledges for proof that the whole Prayer was a Form. Thus <q rend="inline">Chriſt uſed a Form of Prayer on the Croſs (ſaith the Doctor) extracted out of the 22d.<note place="margin">P. 7.</note> Pſalm, which begins, <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi>
               </q> But pray who did extract the Petitions, and put them into a Form for him, and oblige him e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven on that occaſion to uſe no other words, but what were ready provided to his hand.</p>
            <p>In the next Paragraph the Doctor freely grants,<note place="margin">P. 9.</note>
               <q rend="inline">that the Lords Prayer is not only a Form, but alſo a direction to draw other Forms by; ſo that we are not confined to the uſe of this Prayer, but have Liturgies which are drawn up by the Lords Prayer.</q> But if we are not limited to the Lords Prayer, but may uſe <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies which are no other words, but ſuch as are agreeable to it, both as to the Form and Matter of them</hi> (which is but an odd ſort of expreſſion to fall from a Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctor) why may not Miniſters, keeping to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Lords Prayer, uſe other words than thoſe which are in the Liturgy, as well as thoſe who are for Liturgies may uſe other words then thoſe which are in the Lords Prayer? This Conceſſion we have from the Doctor upon his taking notice that Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> had ſaid, that the Lords Prayer was antiently uſed, but not out of any apprehenſion that Chriſt did,<note place="margin">P. 3, 4.</note> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. injoyn his Diſciples to uſe it. Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> ſhews that ſome eminent perſons, both antient and more late Writers, were of this opinion; whether his quoting ſo many for that particular, was to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I leave the indifferent Reader to determine. But becauſe the Doctor ſaith, <hi>Maldonat only tells us,</hi>
               <note place="margin">P. 11.</note> 
               <hi>we are not always bound to uſe thoſe very words.</hi> I would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to take notice, that <hi>Maldonat</hi>'s words are, <hi>Non his neceſſario verbis,</hi> &amp;c. Which I conceive do rather
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56330:9"/> ſignifie, we are not abſolutely bound to uſe thoſe very words at any time. But take the words if you pleaſe, according to the Doctors interpretation, if he think <hi>Maldonat</hi> in the right, provided ſuch a conſtruction may be borrowed for his words, that is, That we are not always bound to uſe our Lords very words; I would gladly know then, how we came to be bound to uſe always other people's words.</p>
            <p>The Doctor next ſpeaks of a Gift of Prayer, which he repreſents, as if we were to underſtand by it, <q rend="inline">an extraordinary aſſiſtance of the Spirit to teach men new words and phraſes in ordinary caſes, and for their dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayers.</q> Whereas by the gift of Prayer, no more is meant, than an Ability to repreſent the ſentiments of a Soul duly affected with the general and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſubject matters of Prayer, in proper and ſuitable expreſſions, and ſuch as are proper to beget, and excite, and improve ſuch Reſentments, and Affections in thoſe who ſhall hear and join in the uſe of them, for that purpoſe. The gift of Prayer, ſoberly conſidered, does not imply any neceſſity (as the Doctor hints) conſtantly to vary, and uſe all new words. Indeed the exerciſe of this gift cannot very well conſiſt with an obligation conſtantly to uſe the very ſame words. Nor is it uſually pretended, that this is an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary gift of the Spirit; but as by the bleſſing of the Spirit, the Heart or Soul comes to have a lively appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, and affectionate ſenſe of what is to be ſubject matter of prayer; ſo the perſon, who is thus inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſpoſed, hath ordinarily a readineſs to expreſs him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in words, which bear ſome proportions to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Soul and Spirit, and which are very proper to kindle and excite the like affections, diſpoſitions, and inclinations in others who do ſeriouſly attend unto
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56330:9"/> them. <q rend="inline">Tho there are ſome particular words very per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to be uſed in prayer for general or particular mercies, yet there may be other words every jot as pertinent, which being uſed as occaſion offers, may be more ſerviceable, and contribute more, to further the common or more appropriate end of Publick Prayer, than the conſtant uſe of the other words.</q> The Lords Prayer doth comprehend the whole of Prayer. But yet thoſe who are moſt for Liturgies, are for having other Forms framed, wherein the ſame things are asked in other words. Now thoſe ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious perſons who pray for the ſame things which are prayed for in preſcribed Forms, without tying themſelves up ſtrictly to the words uſed in thoſe Forms, do differ no more from the Forms which have not their words in them, than thoſe Forms do from the Lords Prayer. And if the variation of Forms from the Lords Prayer may be truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial and advantagious unto the people, why may not the like variations from Humane Forms be equally advantagious? I will propound one thing the more to explain this matter, which more nearly relates to the Doctor. He hath paraphraſed the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Prayers in our <hi>Common-Prayer Book,</hi> ſo that the particular Prayers in that <hi>Book,</hi> are by his labour, and induſtry, and gift, made larger, and expreſſed in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther words. The ſame things are requeſted, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in his larger Prayers, which are requeſted in the ſhorter Prayers in our <hi>Common Book.</hi> Now let him conſider whether he had not ſuch apprehenſions, and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his mind and ſoul, relating to the particulars petitioned, and confeſſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Prayers contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in our <hi>Common Book,</hi> at that time, as he thought might be more commodiouſly and advantagiouſly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed and repreſented, than they were by the words
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56330:10"/> uſed in the <hi>Book?</hi> Or whether ſuch expreſſions did not occur to him, as he thought would, if duly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to, help peoples devotions more, than the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry words of the <hi>Common Prayers</hi> would by themſelves? He certainly had ſome deſign in varying and altering the words; and I am willing to believe he had an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſign. Now if his uſing other expreſſions about the ſame matter, and altering Forms of Prayer, ſo as to make of ſhort Prayers long ones, is of real uſe to promote devotion, why may not others variations be in their meaſure uſeful too? If it ſhould be ſaid, that his variations are not to be uſed publickly, I ask whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be ever the better for that? Or whether his variations are the more uſeful, becauſe only for private uſe? What hinders, but if thoſe variations are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to anſwer the ends for which they were devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>viz.</hi> the helping of people to perform the duty of Prayer with more underſtanding, and better affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, other variations in publick may be equally uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful?</p>
            <p>If,<note place="margin">P. 16.</note> as the Doctor doth grant, <q rend="inline">every good man may by the ordinary aſſiſtance of the ſpirit be moved to pray with <hi>Devotion</hi> and <hi>Fervency:</hi>
               </q> That is (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) may have his ſoul enlightned, and poſſeſſed with a true apprehenſion and knowledge of his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual concernments, and vigorouſly affected with them, and carried out towards God in fervent deſires, incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and affections ſuitably to his preſent occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; What reaſon can be rendered why he may not by the ordinary aſſiſtance of the ſpirit be inabled to expreſs his inward reſentments in proper expreſſions? The gift of utterance being the gift of the ſpirit, as well as other gifts. Mens diſcourſes are uſually anſwerable to their apprehenſions and affections. What we dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apprehend, we expreſs obſcurely: and what we un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56330:10"/> diſtinctly and clearly, we diſcourſe of plainly.</p>
            <p>The principal thing, indeed, in Prayer is the frame and actings of our Souls; the inward exerciſe of Faith, Repentance, Love, and other Graces. <q rend="inline">But, ſaith the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, any good man may act theſe in the uſe of a Form.</q> And therefore may pray in, or by the Spirit in the uſe of a Form. But I ſay it muſt ſtill be noted, that if a man be to pray with others, (and that which we are now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing, is concerning one that by way of Office is to perform this duty in the hearing of others) ſo as to have them joyn with him in this performance, he muſt uſe words, and if he reſtrain himſelf to the words deviſed and put together by others, and theſe words do not ſo well expreſs and repreſent the ſenſe he hath, and which others ſhould have of what is the matter of Prayer, as others which do occur unto him, and which he could very pertinently make uſe of for that purpoſe; he cannot be truly ſaid to pray in or by the Spirit, according to the full import of that phraſe. <q rend="inline">But, ſaith the Doctor, then no man in the Publick Aſſemblies, doth pray in the Spirit, but the Miniſter, for the Miniſter alone conceives the Prayer, and it is a Form to the whole Congregation, who muſt pray in his words.</q> To which I anſwer, That the matter in diſpute at preſent, is only concerning him that offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates. Beſides, it is not a Form to the Congregation, taking a Form in the ſenſe we are now diſcourſing of. But the Congregation may joyn in the Spiritual Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of this Duty, acting graces ſuitably to the occaſions which are adminiſtred, and improving for this purpoſe; the Abilities God hath beſtowed upon others, in order to the furthering and promoting of their devotion. This is the work which pertains unto the Congregation at that time; they not being called to expreſs vocally their inward reſentments, (during
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56330:11"/> the Miniſters officiating in this performance) in the fitteſt expreſſions they are able.</p>
            <p>The Doctor ſeems to be of the opinion, that in the Apoſtles days, there was an extraordinary gift of Prayer which ſome did partake of, and that their Prayers were Divine Revelations. <q rend="inline">They being imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately furniſhed by the Spirit, both with the Matter and Words of their Prayers; and that theſe Prayers were written down, and after that gift failed, they were preſerved and uſed by the Church, and were tranſmitted down to us by their Succeſſors.</q> So that by this ſort of diſcourſing, our Liturgies are Divine Revelations. But the Doctor hath none of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents but St. <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> to vouch for an Extraordinary Gift of Prayer in the Primitive Times. This is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, before the Liturgies now extant, or any part of them which is not expreſly contained in the Books of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> will be owned by good Chriſtians and ſound Proteſtants for Divine Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, very ſubſtantial particular proof muſt be made of their being ſuch. To father Liturgies in ſuch an arrogant preſumptuous manner, on the Holy Spirit, is not the way to bring them into credit with judicious and ſerious people. It may effectually provoke God to pour forth in a little time ſo much contempt upon them, they ſhall never get into repute any more. This is further certain, that our lateſt Liturgies have ſome prayers in them, which by the very make of them, any ordinary perſon may perceive they were not compoſed by Divine Inſpiration. And if the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther could be proved to be of ſuch an original, ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe will not deſerve to be thought the more ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable, meerly becauſe they have been added unto them. Having ſaid thus much concerning ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in the Doctors Introduction, before he enters
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56330:11"/> upon the Firſt Century: I will now briefly conſider the Teſtimonies he doth alledge for Liturgies</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Firſt Century.</head>
               <p>And he labours firſt of all to prove what he hath undertaken,<note place="margin">P. 28, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> by aſſerting that <q rend="inline">the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> (who have been believed by divers learned men to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians) had Forms of Prayer, for <hi>Joſephus</hi> ſaith they uſed Prayers which they received from their Forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which muſt be Forms; and <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith they did ſing alternately; and <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls theſe, the Hymns ſung amongſt us Chriſtians. And that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Hiſtorian labours to prove theſe <hi>Eſſenes</hi> were Chriſtians by this Argument amongſt ſome others, Becauſe they prayed and ſung Hymns in ſet Forms, as the Chriſtians uſe to do.</q>
                  <note place="margin">Euſcb Hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> Thus far the Doctor. And I do readily acknowledge that <hi>Fuſebius</hi> doth indeavour from what he ſinds in <hi>Philo,</hi> to prove the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> to be Chriſtians: And particularly from their way of ſinging Pſalms, and Hymns. But he doth not ſay one word of their having ſet Forms of Prayers: That <hi>they prayed in ſet Forms, as the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians uſe to do,</hi> is the Doctor's own ſaying, for <hi>Fuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> doth neither ſay the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> had Forms of Prayers, nor that the Chriſtians did uſe any. And yet <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> doth ſay, That <hi>Philo</hi>'s Book doth comprehend in it the Rules of the Church. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Valefius</hi> thinks this doth import, that that Book did contain in it all the Rules or Canons which were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Chriſtian Church in <hi>Euſebius</hi>'s time. Further, <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth gather out of that Book what he thought was proper to ſhew how exactly theſe <hi>Eſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> and the Chriſtians did agree in their Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as he himſelf aſſures us in the Chapter before
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56330:12"/> referred unto; And yet ſaith not one word of praying by ſet Forms; which rather intimates there were no ſet Forms of Prayer uſed by the Chriſtians in his time, ſeeing he omits the mention of the Forms the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> uſed, if as <hi>Joſephus</hi> reports the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> had Forms of Prayer.</p>
               <p>In the next place the Doctor thinks he hath a proof of Liturgies in <hi>Clemens Romanus.</hi> But whoever conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders <hi>Clemens,</hi> will ſoon perceive that the paſſages the Doctor hath been pleaſed to quote, are nothing at all to the preſent purpoſe. For <hi>Clemens</hi> had been perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to lead a godly life, and to abſtain from all kinds of vices, and to behave themſelves with ſuch reſpect and kindneſs one towards another, as did become them: And particularly he preſſes them all to obſerve the Offices and Duties which did pertain to them according to their particular ſtations, capacities, conditions, places, gifts, endowments and acquirements, certifying them, that whatever ſtate and condition any man was in, whether he were rich or poor, ſtrong or weak, he had ſome ſpecial buſineſs to mind; or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his endowments and acquirements were, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were wiſe, humble, chaſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Lord, and he muſt give God thanks for them. He ſaith that there is ſome buſineſs and work God hath obliged every man unto, anſwerable to the ſtate and circumſtances he is in; and this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to be ſo, by the Holy Scriptures, we all ought to do the Offices God hath enjoined us, according as our circumſtances are, in the order and manner he hath appointed them to be done. In ſhort, he tells them that people have a dependance one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and God hath provided every man, whatever his condition is, a buſineſs, office and work, (which <hi>Clemens</hi> names <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) which he is to attend unto,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56330:12"/> doing every part of his Work, or Liturgy, in the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner God hath preſcribed, and in the ſeaſon he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and what ever good he doth enjoy, or excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent qualification he is endued with, he is wholly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to God for it, and muſt therefore be careful to give thanks unto him for it. This he confirms, and illuſtrates by ſhewing that among the Jews, the High-prieſt had his buſineſs, and the Prieſts had theirs, and the Levites theirs, and the People had their works, which they were all in their ſeveral ſtations to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend unto and perform; from whence he inforces his exhortation to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that they would all mind their own buſineſs, do the work which God had appointed them in their places, be content with their own ſtation, give God thanks for what they had, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good conſcience, ordering themſelves modeſtly, decently, not tranſgreſſing the bound God had fixed for every perſons Work, Office, or Liturgy;<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. edit. Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt. <hi>pag. 53.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>What the Doctor alledgeth from <hi>Pliny,</hi> refers only to ſinging of Pſalms, or Hymns. Indeed he would fain draw in Prayers along with them, though his Author ſay never a word concerning their Prayers, much leſs that they prayed conſtantly in the uſe of Forms, which were impoſed upon them. The Doctor ſays that <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Plinies</hi> Account agrees exactly with that of the <hi>Eſſenes,</hi> and they having Forms of Prayer, we muſt conclude the Chriſtians had alſo.</q> I inquire not what neceſſity there is to conclude thus. Concerning the <hi>Eſſenes,</hi> and their agreement with the Chriſtians, I have ſpoken already. Nor is <hi>Plinies</hi> Account exact, if we believe the Account <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth give of the <hi>Eſſenes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56330:13"/>
               <p>The Doctor hath but one Author more to quote in this Century for Liturgies, and that is <hi>Ignatius.</hi> And becauſe <hi>Ignatius</hi> hath theſe words,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes he hath a ſolid proof of a fixed Liturgy. But if you conſult <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Epiſt. <hi>ad Magnes.</hi> You will find that the Doctor hath not given the plain ſenſe of the place. He is perſwading them of <hi>Magneſia,</hi> not to be offended with, or contemn their Biſhop, becauſe of his youth, but to reverence him, and adhere firm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his Communion, and come all together <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (tranſlate it how you pleaſe) to Prayer,<note place="margin">Ignat. ad Magnes. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Id.</note> that ſo their Prayer and Supplication might be one. <hi>Ignatius</hi> doth not call their Prayer and Supplication one, becauſe they uſed one Form of Prayer, but on the account of their joyning together in the performance of that Duty. His next quotation out of <hi>Ignatius ad Smirn.</hi> is no more to his purpoſe than the former. Such ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions there are in the Epiſtle as the Doctor doth mention; but I think, if you conſider the Epiſtle you will readily perceive that they do import no more than his declaration, that their Biſhops Communion was Orthodox and Sound, Divine Ordinances being celebrated in his Church as they ought to be; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would have them adhere firmly to his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who will not perform himſelf, or allow o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to perform the Celebration of the Euchariſt or Baptiſm, otherwiſe than the Scripture doth warrant, And all that he ſaith of this kind, is only to ſecure the people from partaking in any adminiſtrations which might be corrupted by thoſe who were infected, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the account he gave in the former part of the Epiſtle. But there is not a word of preſcribed Forms that I can find in the whole Epiſtle.<note place="margin">P. 27.</note> It ſeems a little ſtrange to me, the Doctor ſhould be ſo concerned to have <hi>Ignatius</hi> (according to <hi>Socrates</hi> his Relation) own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56330:13"/> to be <hi>the firſt that brought the uſage of ſinging by way of Antiphone into the Church of</hi> Antioch; And that he ſhould pretend that <hi>Theodoret's ſilence, concerning this matter, might proceed from his taking it for granted, and ſuppoſing it was generall owned and known</hi> For the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of this matter, as it is in <hi>Socrates</hi> is generally, by Learned men, paſſed over as Fabulous and Chimerical; and <hi>Theodoret</hi> is as poſitive, and expreſs that <hi>Flavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> and <hi>Diodorus</hi> were the firſt that brought that way of Singing into that Church, as an Hiſtorian can well be. His words are theſe (ſpeaking of <hi>Flavianus</hi> and <hi>Diodorus</hi>) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodor.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. Hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> And <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſius</hi> certifies that <hi>Theodorus M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pſueſtenus</hi> who lived at the ſame time with <hi>Flavianus</hi> and <hi>Diodorus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Annot.</hi> in lib. <hi>6.</hi> Hiſt. Eccles. <hi>Socrat.</hi> p. <hi>78.</hi>
                  </note> doth teſtifie the very ſame thing, declaring that they had it from the <hi>Syrians.</hi> Having given you this account of the Doctors Quotations out of the Writers in the firſt Century, I will conſider what Evidence he hath for Liturgies</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Second Century.</head>
               <p>The firſt paſſage he alledgeth in this Century is out of <hi>Lucian</hi> (as he truly ſaith) <hi>a jearing Pagan</hi> The Doctor is of opinion that the Religious Aſſembly he deſcribes, was a Chriſtian Church. I think he had a deſign to ridicule all Religious Worſhip, and the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to effect his deſign, he jumbles ſome things in the Chriſtian Worſhip, and ſome things in the Pagan Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together, adding alſo what did occur to him, which he thought would contribute to the rendering of a Religious Aſſembly thoroughly diverting, and grateful to a prophane Gentus.<note place="margin">Lucian <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopat.</hi>
                  </note> The paſſage the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor quotes out of this Author is this; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56330:14"/> 
                  <hi>That Prayer which began with the Father, and ended with the Hymn of many Names.</hi> Now <hi>Lucian</hi> doth not ſay, that he heard this Prayer in that Aſſembly which hath been deſcribed in that Dialogue. But acquaints him, he had brought in relating what paſſed there, that he had not patience to hear any more of that ſort of ſtuff, and that a further diſcourſe about ſuch matters, would have the ſame effect on him, as a ſtory would, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a Prayer beginning and ending as is before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Which though <hi>Julian</hi> might deſign as a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection on the Chriſtians way of Praying, yet for ought I know, it imports no more, than if you ſhould tell me a Story of peoples beginning their Prayer, as if they worſhipped but one perſon, and yet ſhould conclude their Prayer in ſuch a manner, as if they had been Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the while to a great many perſons. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor thinks that <hi>Lucian</hi> doth by this Prayer mean the whole Communion Office. But this is only conjecture. I will ſay no more of that, but only mind you, that when the Doctor ſuſpected his evidence for Liturgies in this Century would not be very clear,<note place="margin">P. 29.</note> he aſſigned this for his Reaſon; <q rend="inline">We have no Authors, who had occaſion to Write particularly of the Church Service, which they cared not to publiſh, leſt the Pagans un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whom they lived, ſhould deride or blaſpheme their Sacred Myſteries.</q> And yet in the next Page, to ſerve a turn we muſt have the moſt jearing Pagan that Age did afford admitted to take a view of their Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration during their whole Communion Office. But ſuppoſe <hi>Lucian</hi> was really at a Chriſtian Aſſembly, and did hear there a Prayer which began with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ended with an acknowledgement of, and an aſcription of Glory and Honour, in variety of expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to every Perſon in the Trinity (as is very uſual with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56330:14"/> thoſe who do not bind themſelves in all their Prayers, to a preciſe number of words) might not he give that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of that Prayer, which is before related, and yet there be no preſcribed Liturgy impoſed on that Aſſembly?</p>
               <p>The next Author, the Doctor hath recourſe unto, is <hi>Juſtin Martyr.</hi> Whether <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> undertaking to write an Apology for the Chriſtians, and in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular for their Church Service, had not occaſion to write particularly of their Church Service, I leave the indiſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and unprejudiced Reader to judge.<note place="margin">P. 31.</note> The Doctor doth acknowledge that <q rend="inline">he doth often ſpeak of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Aſſemblies, and of the ſeveral Duties there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Now if they were tied up to the conſtant uſe of a preciſe number of Words in their Prayers, tho he might not think it convenient to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their words, yet what can be imagined to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his declaring they did celebrate their Offices in ſtinted Forms?<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> But (ſaith the Doctor) <q rend="inline">when <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> mentions Baptiſm, he only faith, They are taught to Faſt and Pray, and ask of God the forgiveneſs of their former Sins, and being brought where water is, they are Regenerated in the ſame manner as we were Regenerated; from whence the Doctor infers, that even in his time they began to conceal the particular manner of Celebrating theſe Myſteries.</q> Now I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Doctor is under ſome miſtake, as to this Paſſage: for <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> doth immediately relate in what manner they were Regenerated.<note place="margin">Juſt. Mar. Apol. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>They are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated in the ſame manner as we were Regenerated; for</hi> (ſaith <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>) <hi>they are then waſhed in Water, in the Name of the Father of all things, and Lord God, and of our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Holy Spirit.</hi> And then he proceeds to ſome extent, in explaining and ſhewing the reaſon of all this; ſo that here appears not any intent that he had, to conceal any thing that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56330:15"/> was in uſe amongſt them. But notwithſtanding <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin Martyr</hi>'s reſervedneſs, in the Doctor's opinion, the Doctor meets <q rend="inline">with ſome general expreſſions which incline him to believe they had Forms in his time. He will not inſiſt upon his ſaying they prayed for the Converſion of the Jews, and the Deliverance of the Gentiles from their errors, and for all men, though theſe are pieces of Antient Litany.</q> I only ask whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things cannot be prayed for, unleſs people be bound up to the conſtant uſe of particular preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed words? And whether there be any evidence that <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> borrowed this account from any Litany?</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">The Doctor next obſerves that when <hi>Juſtin Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> ſpeaks of the bringing the newly Baptized perſon to the place where the Faithful Worſhipped God,<note place="margin">P. 32.</note> he ſaith they there made Common Prayers for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for the perſon Baptized,<note place="margin">Juſt. Mar. <hi>Apol.</hi> 2.</note> and for all other men every where with great fervency.</q> Now (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>Common Prayers do ſignify Forms that are known to all, and in which all may joyn.</hi> But I anſwer, the queſtion is not, what Common Prayers do ſignifie now; but whether <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> did mean ſet preſcribed Forms, which they muſt conſtantly uſe, and from which they muſt not on any account vary? Here doth not appear any thing to incline us to think he meant preſcribed Forms. But his very next words intimate the Reaſon why he called them Common Prayers [They made Common Prayers for themſelves, for the perſon Baptized, and for all other men every where] <hi>viz.</hi> becauſe they did all hold Communion in offering up Prayers to God, and their Prayers were not limited to themſelves, but did extend to the whole Community of Mankind. What the Doctor doth here alledge out of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> hath been conſidered already; what he produceth out of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſhall be conſidered
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:56330:15"/> when I come to his quotations out of that Author, where you will meet again with this ſame paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage.</p>
               <p>In the next place the Doctor reports a paſſage which Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> cites out of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 33.</note> about which they do both make ſome ſtir. The paſſage is this; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The Preſident in like manner offers up Prayers and Thankſgivings, as well as he is able.</hi> Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> urges this as a proof, that he who did officiate in the Publick Worſhip, was not tied up to the uſe of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Forms, but did pray and give thanks according to his ability. And he produceth many teſtimonies to prove that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> here uſed doth import ſo much. The Doctor undertakes to prove that that phraſe doth ſignifie otherwiſe in this place. <q rend="inline">For (ſaith the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> anſwers to <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the place before cited, and that declares the Prayers at Baptiſm (He ſhould have ſaid after Baptiſm) were made ſervently, or with all their might.</q> He endeavours to confirm this interpretation by producing ſome other paſſages, where the phraſe ſeems to be of this importance. And then determines. that <q rend="inline">When we deſire the ſeveral things prayed for in a Form, with all the earneſtneſs and vigor we can, we may properly be ſaid to pray <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as well as we are able, or to the utmoſt of our power. So that the power here ſpoken of, refers to the affections, and not to the phraſes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of him that prays.</q>
               </p>
               <p>To all this I have theſe things to ſay; 1. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> doth not refer us to the paſſage the Doctor hath recourſe to, for the explaining of this phraſe by <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, but doth expreſly refer us to what he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated a little before, where he ſaith the Preſident of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth up Prayers and Praiſes to God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and gives
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56330:16"/> thanks for the benefits and gifts he vouchſafeth in the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which, for any thing I do yet underſtand to the contrary, may ſignifie <hi>largely, diſtinctly, and with variety of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</hi> So that if we muſt interpret <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> by what goeth before in <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> we muſt explain it by this: For this is what <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> doth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly refer us unto in this place. 2. Tho this phraſe doth ſignifie fervently, and ſo refers to the affections, I do not underſtand any reaſon that can pertinently be alledged, why this ſhould exclude him who officiates, from uſing his utmoſt ability to expreſs his inward devotion, in the beſt manner and fitteſt words he can, to help the devotion of thoſe perſons who join with him in the Service. Put the Caſe, a Miniſter doth in Publick uſe a Preſcribed Form of Prayer, and deſires the ſeveral things prayed for in that Form, with all the earneſtneſs and vigour he can; but yet perceives the words of that Form do not repreſent and expreſs his inward reſentments and devout affections in ſo vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid and proper a manner, for the helping and aſſiſting of his hearers devotion, as he is able to repreſent them by his own expreſſions; I dare refer it to the Doctor, whether he may properly be ſaid to pray in the uſe of that Form, as well as he is able, and to the utmoſt of his power. I will allow he doth pray fervently and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voutly; but I think it will be hard to perſwade any man of ſenſe, that he doth pray as well as he is able; unleſs we muſt be forced to grant, that a man may properly be ſaid to pray as well as he is able, tho at the ſame time he is able to pray better than he doth. 3. As for all the quotations the Doctor alledgeth to prove that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth note fervency and vigorous affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: I leave the Doctor to look them over again, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56330:16"/> conſider whether his Authors do mean no more than vigorous affections, and had any deſign to exclude peoples uſing their beſt abilities, for the moſt advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious outward performance of their Work and Duty.</p>
               <p>The Doctor further obſerves,<note place="margin">P. 35.</note> with reference to this paſſage, <q rend="inline">That this phraſe doth only relate to the Hymns uſed in the Euchariſt, and theſe Hymns were known Forms.</q> To which I anſwer? 1. I think it equally relates to the Prayers and Thankſgivings which were celebrated on that occaſion; and I leave any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different perſon, who underſtands the paſſage, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude (when he looks upon it as it lies in the Author) as lie ſhall ſee reaſon, whether it doth relate more to the one, than to the other. 2. Tho Hymns may be, and often are uſed for celebrating the praiſes of God, yet that is not the only way whereby we may offer up our Praiſes and Thankſgivings to God. 3. <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſpeaks here expreſly of the Preſidents offering up particular thanks for the benefits exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and vouchſafed in the <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> and ſpeaks of his performing the Offices of Prayer and Praiſe himſelf, without any audible concurrence of the people during the whole Service. Yea, he further acquaints us, that when the Preſident hath finiſhed theſe Offices, then it is the people do ſpeak, teſtifying their joyful approbation by ſaying <hi>Amen.</hi> This is the account he gives us himſelf of this matter but a very little before the paſſage now inſiſted on, and whither he refers us in this very place, for the more diſtinct apprehending of his meaning here.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">But, ſaith the Doctor,<note place="margin">P. 36.</note> all Chriſtians are ſaid to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God and his Son, according to their ability, with Prayer and Praiſe; and private Chriſtians we may be ſure were not allowed to make their own Prayers
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56330:17"/> and Praiſes in Publick Worſhip <hi>extempore.</hi>
                  </q> To this I anſwer, That the matter in diſpute at preſent, is concerning him that Officiates. And all the ſtir which is made about this phraſe, in the preſent caſe, amounts (I think) to no more than this, whether a Miniſter may properly be ſaid to pray to the utmoſt of his ability, when he doth not pray to the utmoſt of his ability: Which in my apprehenſion is a very plain caſe, if people were free from prejudice. Well, but it may be enquired how the people can be ſaid in the Publick Worſhip to pray according to the utmoſt of their abilities? I anſwer their circumſtances are not the ſame with his, who is to officiate; And therefore this phraſe hath not the ſame importance when appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the one, and when extended to the other. The people are ſaid to pray to God, and to praiſe him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the utmoſt of their ability in the Publick Worſhip, when they do make the beſt improvement they can, of the uſe he who doth officiate, doth make of the abilities he is indued with for the celebrating of theſe Offices, to the furthering of their own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion.</p>
               <p>There is one thing more the Doctor doth take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of, with reference to the phraſe we have been diſcourſing of.<note place="margin">P. 38.</note> And that is this; He ſaith, <q rend="inline">We are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider this phraſe here, as it is applied to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and praiſing God. And there it never ſignifies doing theſe things <hi>extempore</hi>
                  </q> (he ſhould have ſaid according to the beſt of thoſe abilities with which God hath endued them, who are to celebrate theſe Offices) <q rend="inline">but doing them very devoutly.</q> Now whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inward devotion in theſe Services be all this phraſe doth import, with reference to them who are to Officiate, I refer to what I have already ſaid about that matter. I will further only mind you, that tho
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56330:17"/> the Doctor hath taken notice of ſome of the quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> hath produced for the ſignification of this phraſe in other caſes, yet he hath not ſaid one word here by way of reply to thoſe inſtances Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> hath given, expreſly relating to the caſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he doth acknowledge the phraſe is at preſent to be conſidered. The inſtances Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> hath produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, relating to Prayer and Praiſe, you may find in the 118, 119, 120 pages of his Diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Liturgies.</p>
               <p>The Doctor having done with <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds to <hi>Ireneus,</hi> out of whom he alledgeth only one paſſage, which is,<note place="margin">P. 39.</note> that <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Ireneus</hi> relates that the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, to prove their phancies, did alledge that we (that is, the Orthodox) in our Thankſgivings, do ſay world without end.</q> From hence the Doctor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that <q rend="inline">theſe words being the very concluſion of the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> the Chriſtians praiſed God in publick by this very Form which we now uſe; Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry be to the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Now, allowing the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did uſually in his time uſe this Doxology, how will this prove they were ſtinted in their Publick Worſhip to a preſcribed Liturgy? But according to my apprehenſion, this is no proof, that this Doxolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy was then in uſe; unleſs it can be made appear, that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, cannot conclude any Praiſe and Thankſgiving but this Doxology. The buſineſs in ſhort is thus; <hi>Ireneus</hi> is ſhewing how abſurdly thoſe Hereticks did endeavour to prove their conceit of their <hi>Aeones,</hi> which was by urging every ſentence where they found the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as a proof of what they aſſerted. Amongſt other things they pleaded that the Orthodox did uſually conclude their Praiſes with ſaying, for ever and ever, or as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor will have it, world without end.<note place="margin">Iren. adv. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:56330:18"/> Now all that can fairly be inferred from hence, I think, is this, that the Chriſtians did uſually conclude their Praiſes with theſe words, for ever and ever. And if no Prayers or Praiſes but preſcribed Forms can conclude with theſe words, I am contented that this ſhould paſs for a proof of ſtinted Forms in <hi>Ireneus</hi> his time. But if Prayers and Praiſes, which are not Preſcribed Forms, may conclude, and ordinarily are concluded with theſe words, I leave the Doctor to conſider whether his alledging this for a proof of a fixed Liturgy, be not a way of arguing very like that which was uſed by thoſe <hi>Ireneus</hi> did write againſt? <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſhall be conſidered when he comes in order, and then you may judge of the Doctors Inference.</p>
               <p>The next Author the Doctors makes uſe of,<note place="margin">P. 40.</note> is <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> Out of whom a paſſage is quoted, concerning which he and Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> do differ, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meaning of it.<note place="margin">Clem. Alex. Strom. <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> The paſſage is this; <hi>The Church is not only the name of the place for Publick Worſhip, but the Congregation proſtrating themſelves in Prayers, having all, as it were, one common voice, and one mind.</hi> The diſpute is concerning the meaning of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> thought the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation had one voice in reſpect of the Miniſters ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their ſtead, one for all. <q rend="inline">The Doctor thinks it ſignifies the performing the Offices of Prayer and Praiſe in a reſponſory way, which muſt be in known Forms, becauſe the people not only joined in heart with the Miniſter, but vocally anſwered in their turns, they and the Prieſt often making up the ſentence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them; and therefore they are ſaid to have, <hi>as it were.</hi> one common voice.</q> I leave the Learned to determine which of them is in the right, as to the ſenſe of this phraſe: And will only acquaint you, that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56330:18"/> I think, if the way of Reſponſory Prayers, and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, had been antecedently proved to be the ordinary way of the Chriſtian Church in the Primitive Ages, there would have been ſomething to countenance the Doctors interpretation. But to interpret this place thus, can be no proof for Liturgies, becauſe the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation is built upon a ſuppoſition, and takes that for granted, which it is alledged to prove. Beſides, if the people did vocally anſwer in their turns, and they and the Prieſt did often make up the ſentence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, as the Doctor affirms; I think in thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they could hardly be ſaid to have, as it were, one common voice, for they would evidently have two common voices. The Prieſt having one common voice for himſelf and them, in his part of the ſentence, and the People another common voice, for themſelves and the Prieſt, in their part of the ſentence. It does indeed exceed my reach to comprehend a Reaſon why the Congregation may not be ſaid to have one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon voice in Prayer and Praiſe, when they have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed or choſen a Prieſt to officiate in their name, and do concur and join with him in thoſe Offices. No nor why they may not be ſaid to have, as it were, one common voice, in the Doctors notion of that phraſe, when they do teſtifie their approbation of what he hath ſaid (as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> aſſures us they did) by ſaying <hi>Amen.</hi> But, ſaith the Doctor <q rend="inline">If the Miniſter had ſaid all the Prayers, he, (i. e. <hi>Clemens</hi>) muſt have ſaid plainly, they had one common mouth, or voice, but his words are, having, <hi>as it were,</hi> one common voice.</q> I leave you to conſider, whether their anſwering <hi>Amen</hi> is not enough to remove this ſcruple. Only you may take notice that the Doctor is of opinion that <hi>Clemens</hi> doth allude here to thoſe words of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 15.6. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:56330:19"/> there of glorifying God with one mouth, not, <hi>as it were</hi> with one mouth. The Doctor further obſerves from <hi>Clemens,</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">that the Chriſtians allotted ſeveral hours for Prayer, in imitation of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Jews,</hi> and hence concludes it likely, that becauſe the <hi>Jews</hi> had Forms of Prayer, they did imitate them in theſe too.</q> I think it needleſs to make any Reply to this, becauſe it is a forced way of reaſoning, and is at beſt, all over meer conjecture. But, ſaith the Doctor, <q rend="inline">would thoſe who prayed ſo often, vary the phraſe every time?</q> Now this is not at all to the point, for that which the Doctor ſhould prove, is, that they were obliged conſtantly to uſe the very ſame words. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor further tells us, <q rend="inline">That <hi>Clemens</hi> doth not relate what were the words of their Forms.</q> There the Doctor ſpeaks very right, but withall I muſt add, he never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates that they had any Forms. But <hi>Clemens</hi> tells us what were their main Petitions. And the Doctor ſaith, <q rend="inline">Theſe matters they asked, were ſuch, it was moſt fit to ask them in a ſet Form of words.</q> That is one Doctors opinion. But if the Chriſtians of that Age were of another opinion, what becomes of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors argument? And he muſt give ſome evidence they were of his opinion, before what he aſſerts will paſs for proof in the preſent caſe. But, ſaith the Doctor, <q rend="inline">If they had prayed for theſe things <hi>extempore, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> could not be ſo poſitive in the method as he ſeems to be.</q> To which I make this reply, <hi>viz. Clemens</hi> reports the methods of Chriſtians private de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions every jot as particularly, as that quotation he inſiſts on, with relation to Publick Prayers, doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late their method: Whether that I ſpeak of be the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſame the Doctor refers unto, I will not affirm, but it ſeems to have ſome affinity, and I am ſure it is in the ſame Book his Margin refers to. If it ſhould be
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:56330:19"/> the ſame the Doctor means, you will eaſily perceive how little it is to his purpoſe. And why ſhould the Doctor think it ſtrange. <hi>Clemens</hi> could be ſo poſitive (as naming three general heads of Prayer doth amount to) in the method of their Publick Prayers: tho they did not uſe a fixed preſcribed Liturgy? Seeing he is every jot as poſitive in the method of their Private Prayers, unleſs they all uſed the ſame Forms in private too? The truth of which I am perſwaded the Doctor hath no inclination to undertake.<note place="margin">Strom. lib. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>665.</hi>
                  </note> Now <hi>Clemens</hi> tells us that the true Chriſtian, [or as he terms him, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>doth pray every hour. And that he doth firſt ask remiſſion of ſin; then that he may not ſin again; then, that he may do well, and underſtand both Creation and Providence; and that his Heart being made clean by the Knowledge which he hath by the Son of God, he may attain to ſee God face to face.</hi> Such a paſſage as this relating to Publick Prayers out of one of the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, would be look'd on by ſome men, as a ſwing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proof of a preſcribed Liturgy. I leave you to divert your ſelf with the Doctor's dextrous device, to furniſh people with an Expedient to enable them to Pray by Book, with their Eyes and Hands lift up to Heaven.</p>
               <p>The Doctor hath one Author more, whom he quotes in this <hi>Century,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 43.</note> and that is <hi>Tertullian</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">In whoſe works (he ſaith) we have ſufficient evidence that they uſed Forms of Prayer and Praiſe.</q> The paſſages he is concerned with out of this Author, are of two ſorts. 1. Such as he alledgeth to prove the uſe of a Liturgy at that time. 2. Such as Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> produceth to prove the contrary, which the Doctor endeavoureth to make appear, do not anſwer the end for which that Author brings them. I will firſt conſider the paſſages the Doctor alledgeth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:56330:20"/> as ſufficient evidence that the Chriſtians uſed Publick Forms of Prayer and Praiſe in his time. His firſt proof is this; That <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> declares, That Chriſt hath fixed a new Form of Prayer for us, who are his Diſciples, <hi>viz.</hi> The Lords Prayer, which he expounds in a peculiar Tract, and in divers places calls it <hi>The Lawful and the Ordinary Prayer.</hi>
                  </q> I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Tertullian</hi> near the beginning of his Book, <hi>De Oratione,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. de Orat. p. <hi>788.</hi>
                  </note> hath this paſſage; — <hi>Jeſus Chriſtus Demi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Noſter, nobis Diſcipulis Novi Teſtamenti, Novam Orationis Formam determinavit.</hi> The Great Queſtion is, What <hi>Tertullian</hi> did mean by <hi>Novam Orationis For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam?</hi> The Doctor ſaith it was the Lords Prayer, which he expounds in a peculiar Tract. I think his meaning was otherwiſe; And that he did intend no more by that Phraſe, than a new Inſtruction or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection how to perform the Duty of Prayer, which he ſaith was neceſſary to the Goſpel State or Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration: <hi>Oportebat enim in hac quoque ſpecie No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vum Vinum novis utribus recondi.</hi> And though <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> doth expound the Lords Prayer in that Tract, yet he doth conſider it in his explaining of it, not as the whole he underſtands by his <hi>Nova Forma,</hi> but as an inſtance and example of one of the General Inſtructions our Saviour had laid down for the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of us in the performance of this Duty. He doth in a little time, even before he begins his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of the Lords Prayer, alter his phraſe, and calls it <hi>Orandi Diſciplina.</hi> And then tells us this New Way or Inſtruction for Prayer, did conſiſt of ſeveral parts. The third he mentions is <hi>Brevity:</hi> Which he explains by our not laying any ſtreſs on the uſe of a confuſed heap of words, but our uſing ſuch words as are proper and very comprehenſive. And then he certifies us, that our Lord hath given us an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56330:20"/> example of this Brevity, which is the third part of his <hi>Nova Orationis Forma,</hi> or the Third Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept Chriſt injoined to be obſerved in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of this Duty. <hi>Et tamen Brevitas ista, quod ad tertium Sophiae Gradum faciat, magnae ac beatae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretationis ſubſtantia ſulta eſt.</hi> And his principal buſineſs in his expounding the Lord's Prayer, (which he immediately ſubjoins) is to ſhew how compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive our Saviour was in this Prayer, tho it was ſo ſhort, or conſiſted of ſo few words. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth expound every part of the Lords Prayer, yet he doth not ſtrictly tie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the method obſerved in the Lord's Prayer. As for <hi>Tertullians Legitima &amp;, Ordinaria Oratio,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. p. <hi>791.</hi>
                  </note> it ſeems to be juſt the ſame with his <hi>Ordinata Religio Orationis.</hi> Which I conceive is another phraſe of the ſame import with his <hi>Nova Orationis Forma,</hi> and his <hi>Orandi Diſciplina.</hi> Which (I think) do only ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the General Inſtructions Chriſt gave for the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of his Diſciples, or the directing of Chriſtians, in their performing of this Duty of Prayer.</p>
               <p>The Doctors next quotation out of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is of no uſe to the preſent purpoſe, till it be proved that people cannot join in prayer with him who officiates, unleſs they do uſe their voices, during that perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, as audibly, as he doth his, or at leaſt till the pretended implication of their joining voices be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cleared, than by bare aſlertion. But, ſaith the Doctor, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> deſcribes ſome of the things,<note place="margin">P 44.</note> which they deſired of God to beſtow on the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, <hi>viz.</hi> that they might have a long Life, a quiet Empire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> To which I anſwer, that this may paſs for a proof of a fixed Litany, when it ſhall be made evident, that the particulars mentioned by <hi>Tertullian</hi> cannot be prayed for, but in preſcribed words, or that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:56330:21"/> an account cannot be given of the things which are conſtantly prayed for, unleſs thoſe matters be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly prayed for in the ſame preciſe words. But you may take notice that <hi>Tertullian,</hi> when he relates what the Chriſtians prayed for, doth not always uſe the ſame words, nor make the ſame enumeration of particulars. For a proof of this I refer you to <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> himſelf, in the places of his Apology. The Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor refers to, <hi>p.</hi> 44. But if you conſult <hi>Tertullian,</hi> according to the worſer Edition, which is that I am neceſſitated to uſe, you muſt look <hi>p.</hi> 876, and 867. As for the Doctors quotation out of <hi>Tertullian, De Anima.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 142.</note> I need not ſay any thing concerning it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> hath expreſly anſwered the Plea made from that place, and the Doctor hath not thought fit to ſay one word to his vindication of that place. The Doctor's next quotation is out of <hi>Tertullian De Baptiſmo.</hi> Concerning which I ſhall only tell you, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> is replying to thoſe who pretended that Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm is not neceſſary, becauſe Faith is ſufficient. Now amongſt other things <hi>Tertullian</hi> doth urge the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Baptiſm from Chriſts inſtituting of it. <hi>Lex e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim tingendi impoſita eſt, &amp; forma praeſcripta,</hi> ſaith he. And this he proves by producing what is ſaid touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this matter in the laſt Chapters of St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and St. <hi>Mark.</hi> What he ſaith amounts to this; Baptiſm is neceſſary, now under the Goſpel, becauſe the Lord Jeſus hath commanded it, and told us in what manner it is to be adminiſtred. You may try your own faculty, and ſee whether from theſe premiſes, Chriſt hath inſtituted Baptiſm, and hath ſhewn in what manner it muſt be celebrated, you can draw ſuch a concluſion as this, Therefore Prayer and Praiſes are to be performed in the Church by preſcribed Forms, or that <hi>Tertullian</hi> did think ſo, or
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:56330:21"/> that in his days, the Church did worſhip God in the uſe of ſuch preſcribed Liturgies, as is the Subject of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſcourſe. What the Dr. refers us to in <hi>Tertul ad ux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or.</hi> it only concerns ſinging, which is not to our preſent purpoſe. Beſides, if I miſtake not, it only relates to ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Family. The words in <hi>Tertullian</hi> are theſe; <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant inter duos Pſalmi &amp; Hymni,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 534.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; mutuo provocant quis me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Deo ſuo canet. Tertullian</hi> is repreſenting ſome of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages which accrue from Chriſtians Marrying with Chriſtians, and this is one of them.<note place="margin">P 35.</note> But ſaith the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, <q rend="inline">One of theſe Forms was the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> which he deſcribes as <hi>Ireneus</hi> did by the laſt words, <hi>World without end.</hi>
                  </q> Now you muſt take notice that <hi>Tertulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> in this laſt quotation is quite upon another Subject. And the quotation is out of another Book, his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>de Spectaculis.</hi> I will not ſtay to conſider <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullians</hi> ſenſe exactly in this place. He is diſſuading the Chriſtians from frequenting the Heatheniſh Games, Exerciſes, and Shows, and repreſents to them how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming them it muſt needs be, yea how ſinful to concur with them in what did ordinarily paſs on thoſe occaſions.<note place="margin">Tertul. <hi>de Spect.</hi> p. 700.</note> 
                  <hi>Avertat Deus à ſuis tantam voluptatis exiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſae cupiditatem. Quale eſt enim, de Eccleſia Dei in diaboli eccl ſiam terd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re? de coelo (quod aiunt) in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num? illas manus quas ad Dominum extuleris, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dum laudando hiſtrionem fatigare, ex ore quo Amen in ſanctum pretuleris, gladiatori teſtimonium reddere,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>alii omnino dicere niſi Deo Chriſto?</hi> Now how come theſe words of <hi>Tertullian</hi> to be a proof of Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church? Why the Doctor tells us we here find <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; therefore there muſt needs be a Form, and this Form muſt be the <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> becauſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is in the end of that Doxology. the Doctor had told us before that <hi>Irenius</hi> had reference to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:56330:22"/> 
                  <hi>Gloria Patri,</hi> becauſe he found in him <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and here <hi>Tertullian</hi> muſt needs refer to the ſame, becauſe in him we have nothing but <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Can <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be never uſed but in the <hi>Gloria Patri?</hi> I think <hi>Tertullian</hi> is not minding them that this was an expreſſion the Chriſtians did conſtantly uſe in their pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, though it might be conſtantly uſed in their publick Worſhip, and their Worſhip not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in preſcribed Forms; but he rather intimates that this was an expreſſion which was ordinarily uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at thoſe ſights and exerciſes he is diſſuading them from, and that it is not an expreſſion fit for them to uſe with reference unto any but God and Chriſt. But becauſe the Doctor doth lay ſuch ſtreſs on this Phraſe, he may conſider whether the Latin Church did uſe the <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> in Greek in <hi>Tertullians</hi> days?</p>
               <p>Theſe are the paſſages the Doctor thought fit to alledge out of <hi>Tertullian</hi> for what he propounds. The other ſort of paſſages he is concerned with, are ſuch as Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> alledged for what he had aſſerted. There are two of theſe the Doctor doth take notice of, but ſaith ſo little concerning them, I will paſs them over without ſaying any thing of them one way or another; for any one who conſiders what Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> ſaith with reference to them, and what the Doctor ſaith of them here, may eaſily determine whether the paſſages do make more for the one or for the other. But there is one paſſage Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> doth quote from this Author, about which the Doctor takes a great deal of pains,<note place="margin">P. 47, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> to ſhew it is capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of an interpretation which will not ſerve Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi>'s purpoſe. I will relate the paſſage, and without reflecting on the laboured conſtructions the Doctor
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:56330:22"/> hath heaped together, to render it uſeleſs to Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> deſign, I will plainly acquaint you with what I conceive to be the ſureſt way to find out <hi>Tertullians</hi> meaning. The paſſage is this; <hi>Manibus expanſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul</hi> Apol.</note> 
                  <hi>quia innocuis, capite undo, quia non erubeſcimus, denique; ſine monitore, quia de pectore oramus. Tertullian,</hi> I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, doth here give an account of the Chriſtians Prayers, that they were not ſuch as the Heathens were, but ſuch as did ſuit and agree with the advice and direction the Apoſtle had given concerning this buſineſs. His words ſeem to give an account, of what he underſtood to be the Apoſtles meaning, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.8. where he <hi>willeth men to Pray every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath and doubting.</hi> But the Doctor thinks the paſſage is obſcure. If ſo, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>Tertullian</hi> is ſitteſt to give an account of his own meaning; and I think he doth ſo, in a very few lines after: For having ſhewed why he, and ſo all Chriſtians could not pray to any but God, he ſeems very plainly to explain in other words, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral branches of the forementioned account concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chriſtians Prayers. — <hi>Ei offero opimam &amp; majorem hoſtiam, quàm ipſe mandavit, orationem de car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pudica, de anima innocenti, de ſpiritu ſancto profectam.</hi> This I take to be the true account of this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted paſſage; whether I am in the right or not concerning it, I leave you to judge, as alſo whether this paſſage ſo underſtood, do make more for or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt preſcribed Forms of Prayer. Theſe being the paſſages made uſe of from the Authors in the ſecond Century about Liturgies, I proceed to the</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:56330:23"/>
               <head>Third Century.</head>
               <p>In which the firſt Author the Doctor doth quote is <hi>Hippolytus.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 54.</note> The paſſage is this; <hi>Liturgy ſhall be extinguiſhed, ſinging of Pſalms ſhall ceaſe, and reading of Scripture ſhall not be heard.</hi> What <hi>Hippolytus</hi> his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing here is, I will not undertake to affirm poſitively, becauſe I never read that Author. But as ſeeing the Doctor doth argue from the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mind you that the Doctor doth acknowledg it is but probable, that this Father meant a common Form of Prayer generally uſed. And I do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it would be more probable that that Father un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the word in the Doctors ſenſe, if he had produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced any proof that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> did either before, or in the days of this Father ever ſignifie a common Form of Prayer generally uſed in the Chriſtian Church. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed I am not aware that any thing more can be warrantably concluded from this expreſſion, than that Antichriſt would ſuppreſs the publick pure Worſhip of God. And why Antichriſt may not as well ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the publick exerciſe of Miniſters gifts and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in the Worſhip of God, as the uſe of preſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Forms of Prayer, doth not yet occur unto me. But if Antichriſt have already made any attempts againſt the publick Worſhip of God, I muſt needs ſay, I do not remember any evidence he hath given of his extraordinary diſlike of Forms of Prayer, meerly as Forms. Nor do I mind any proof that hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced that <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> did about the Year 220. ſignifie publick preſcribed Forms.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">Our next Author (ſaith the Doctor) <hi>is the Famous Origen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 55.</note> in whoſe eleventh Homily on <hi>Jer.</hi> we have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:56330:23"/> ſo expreſs a Form of Prayer, which was wont to be uſed in his days, the learned <hi>Centuriators</hi> were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by it, that ſet Forms of Prayer were uſed in his time.</q> The matter in debate is not whether thoſe learned men were convinced from that paſſage, that ſet Forms of Prayer were uſed in his time; But whether that paſſage is a ſubſtantial proof, that the Chriſtian Church did in <hi>Origens</hi> time worſhip God only by a preſcribed Liturgy. Now the Argument from this Homily to prove a ſtated Liturgy, depends (as Mr <hi>Clarkſon</hi> ſaith) on the Mode or Form of expreſſion here uſed;<note place="margin">P. 141.</note> and what <hi>Origens</hi> way of expreſſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in this place was, we have not any certainty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have not his own words here, but his Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlator's, who have certified us they did not tie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to an exact and ſtrict tranſlation. This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefore cannot be convincing in the preſent caſe, becauſe we have no aſſurance of the truth and certainty of that, on which the Argument de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, and from which it muſt derive its whole ſtrength. The Doctor doth not take notice of this, but ſuggeſts it is pretended that <hi>Ruſſinus</hi> might add this Prayer himſelf. But the doubt is not ſo much whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he added the Prayer, as whether he did not alter the Mode of expreſſion, and in his Tranſlation put that into the Form of a Prayer, which <hi>Origen</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded in another Form? For tho <hi>Origen</hi> might only relate, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.16, 17. what was the ordinary ſubject of their Petitions on ſuch occaſions, <hi>Ruffinus</hi> might in his Tranſlation deliver it in the Form of a Prayer. And till we have ſome aſſurance that <hi>Origen</hi> is here faithfully tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and did expreſs himſelf exactly in the ſame Mode the Tranſlator reports this matter, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:56330:24"/> cannot be convincing to the purpoſe for which it is brought. Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> further adds, <q rend="inline">That allow all that can be pretended fairly from this place, no more can be concluded from it, than what is common with thoſe who do pray <hi>extempore, viz</hi> that they often in Prayer preferred one or two Petitions in the ſame words.</q> To which the Doctor hath not thought fit to make any reply. If thoſe who do officiate, do frequently uſe the ſame words in Prayer concerning the ſame matter, is the inference thence juſt, that therefore they may not uſe any words, or that they are bound up to a preſcribed Liturgy in their whole worſhip? But having ſaid thus much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Diſpute betwixt the Doctor and Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> touching this paſſage, I will relate the matter it ſelf more diſtinctly. <hi>Origen</hi> having taken notice in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Homily, that the Prophets having ſuffered many hardſhips from the People, on the account of the meſſages they did bring them, and the threatnings they denounced againſt them from the Lord, it was expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient that thoſe who hear the word ſhould be briefly admoniſhed what manner of lives the Prophets did lead, and what benefits did appertain unto them, and what their own duty is, <hi>viz</hi> that if they would partake of the happineſs the Prophets have arrived at, they muſt diligently endeavour to do the works they did. And in ſhort, he adds, his meaning is thus;<note place="margin">Orig. Hom XI. in Jer.</note> 
                  <hi>Frequenter in Oratione dicimus. Da Omnipotens, Da nobis partem cum Prophetis, &amp;c. O Almighty, grant, grant unto us a part with the Prophets, grant us a part with the Apoſtles of thy Chriſt, grant that we may be found at the footſteps of thy only begotten.</hi> But (ſaith he) when we ſpeak theſe things, we do not underſtand, or we have not a due ſenſe of what theſe Petitions do im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:56330:24"/> For in reality, when we ſpeak thus, we do ask that God would make us to be hated as they were hated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now the matter ſeems very plain, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Origen</hi> expounding the Scripture popularly, took occaſion to mind the people how careful they ſhould be, if they deſired to be happy as the Prophets are, to live ſuch lives as they did, and not content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſaying (as was very uſual for them when they heard affectionate diſcourſes concerning the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Lord give us a part with them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For, ſaith he, theſe Petitions or Prayers we are ſo prone to uſe when our affections are mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at the reports which are made to us concerning the Prophets, do properly ſignifie what we do not at all think of, or really intend, when we uſe thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions. For theſe Prayers do really ſignifie our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring of God, that we may be hated as the Prophets were, and fall into the ſame calamities they did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure. <hi>Re enim hoc dicimus, fac nos ſic odio haberi, ut edio habiti ſunt Prophetae; — Da in iſtas incidere ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitates quas Apoſtoli ſuſtinuerunt.</hi> Is it any proof that he who adminiſters Divine Ordinances is tied up to a fixed Liturgy, becauſe in his popular diſcourſes on par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular occaſions, in his preſſing people to a good life, he tells them, we do ordinarily pray, O Almighty, grant us this, or that, or the other thing, and that theſe Petitions are of ſuch importance as to ingage our endeavours to lead ſuch lives as we are perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded unto? Yea, it may be, if the matter be well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired into, it will be found that <hi>Origen</hi>'s explication of this Prayer, is a more juſt reproof of the Prayer it ſelf, than his relating it, is a proof of the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrators being tied up to the uſe of Forms in his time. For it may be very well queſtioned, whether Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:56330:25"/> may pray for what he ſaith thoſe Petitions do properly import.</p>
               <p>The next paſſage the Doctor doth quote out of <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 58.</note> is in his ſixth Book againſt <hi>Celſus;</hi> And he places the force of this quotation on the Participle [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] which he finds in it, and of which he gives this account, that <q rend="inline">it ſignifies not only a thing injoined or commanded in general, but ſo injoined that the very order and manner of doing it, is ſet down and particularly appointed.</q> And I may truly ſay that all this may be with reference unto Prayers, and yet the very words to be uſed, not be ſet down, and particularly appointed, without which there is no Liturgy in our preſent acceptation of that word. But, ſaith the Doctor, <q rend="inline">
                     <hi>Origen</hi> is ſpeaking of the Prayers themſelves, and gives them this Character, that they were ordered or preſcribed, and therefore muſt be in Forms.</q> To which I anſwer, that all he ſaith (except his inference) doth amount to no more than an order for the method of the performance, but doth not reach to the preſcribing of the words. And if God have not only commanded us to pray, but hath alſo given Rules for the manner of performing this Duty, when we perform this Service according to the Rules he hath appointed, we may properly be ſaid to uſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. But if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the paſſage intirely as <hi>Origen</hi> hath it (for the Doctor hath left ſomething out) it will clear it ſelf. <hi>We do affirm for a certain truth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Origen</hi>) <hi>that they who do worſhip God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Orig. in Celf. lib <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the Lord of all things through Jeſus in the Chriſtian manner or way, and hee according to the Goſpel, uſing frequently, as they ought night and day</hi> [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>ſuch Prayers as are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or commanded, are not vanquiſhable, or cannot beover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:56330:25"/> either by Magicians or Devils.</hi> Theſe laſt words the Doctor thought fit to leave out. Now let any one judge, whether by uſing appointed Prayers, <hi>Origen</hi> meant offering up to God Prayers in ſuch way as he had appointed, or uſing ſuch prayers as were compoſed by Men, and ſaying them over in ſuch order as they had preſcribed; which of theſe do you imagine <hi>Origen</hi> thought to be the Chriſtian's effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſecurity from Magicians and Devils? Can it enter into any Mans head, who knows any thing of <hi>Origen,</hi> that he was for Chriſtians to uſe Prayers, as others did Spells? How came the uſe of preſcribed Forms to be better ſecurity from Magicians and Devils, than any other way of praying?</p>
               <p>There is further a Diſpute betwixt the Doctor and Mr. <hi>Clarkſon,</hi> whether <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 61.</note> quoting ſome paſſages which are in the Pſalms, did, by ſaying, we find them <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, mean the publick Liturgy, or the Pſalter? To which I ſhall only ſay, That I do not perceive that there is any Antecedent proof, that they had a publick Liturgy, but it is certain they had the Book of Pſalms amongſt them. I leave you to determine whether it is moſt probable that <hi>Origen,</hi> being to quote Paſſages which were in the Book of Pſalms, would rather refer his Reader to another Book, than unto that which was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be divinely inſpired?</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> is next brought by the Doctor as a Witneſs for Liturgies. And I might ſuppoſe,<note place="margin">P. 65.</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">That he did allow the Lord's Prayer to be uſed as a Form of Prayer, and that he would have us repeat the very words of it:</q> And yet this will not amount to any reſemblance of a proof for Liturgies, as they are here to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:56330:26"/> But the Paſſages in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> the Doctor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth, do not (I think) import what he pretends they do. St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in his Sermon concerning the Lord's Prayer, ſeems to have the very ſame Notions about it, his Maſter <hi>Tertullian</hi> had expreſſed in his Tract concerning the ſame matter, of which I have ſpoken: before. There are indeed ſome Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Sermon, from which the Doctor doth draw his own inferences. The enquiry muſt be, whether St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s meaning in thoſe paſſages was what the Doctor pretends?</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath this Paſſage:<note place="margin">Cypr. Serm. de Orat. Dom.</note> 
                  <hi>Orandi ipſe formam dedit, ipſe quid precaremur monuit &amp; inſtruxit.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive he means no more than this, That the Lord Jeſus hath taught People in what manner they ſhould pray, and what things they ſhould pray for. I think if we conſider St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Diſcourſe, we cannot warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably underſtand any thing elſe by his <hi>Orandi forma,</hi> than thoſe Inſtructions our Saviour gave for our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in performing of this duty of Prayer. St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> doth alſo certifie, that the ſureſt way to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain acceptance and audience with the Father, is to govern our ſelves in the performance of this Duty by the directions the Son hath given for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t dum prece &amp; oratione quam filius docuit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id.</note> 
                  <hi>apud patrem faciliùs audiamur.</hi> If we ſtrictly conſider this Father's ſenſe and meaning, there doth not appear any ground to conclude that he laid any ſtreſs on our uſing the very words of which the Lord's Prayer doth conſiſt. And beſides ſeveral paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages which might be inſtanced in, which do ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intimate that what I have already mentioned, is the ſubſtance of this Father's meaning here, there is one
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:56330:26"/> ſhort Paſſage, at a little diſtance from theſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready mentioned, which, to me, ſeems to put the matter out of all doubt: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t aliter orare quàm docuit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id.</note> 
                  <hi>non ignorantia ſola ſit, ſed &amp; culpa.</hi> Now let any man, who knows any thing at all of St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he thought that it was a ſin to uſe any other words in Prayer, than juſt thoſe which were expreſſed in the Lord's Prayer; and whether his meaning was not, that it is a ſin or fault to govern our ſelves in the performing of this duty, by other Inſtructions, than thoſe the Son had given for our guidance in this Duty? This I take to be the meaning of that other Paſſage, <hi>Agnoſcat pater filii ſui verba, cum precem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus.</hi> By <hi>cerba filii ſui,</hi> I conceive is not meant the words of the Lord's Prayer, but the Inſtructions and Directions the Son gave for the right performing of this duty. Here I may mind you, that the Doctor in his Diſcourſe on one of his Quotations out of <hi>Origen,</hi> hath this Paſſage: <q rend="inline">Note alſo <hi>Origen</hi> doth not ſay,<note place="margin">P. 60.</note> the Chriſtian made theſe injoyned Prayers, but uſed them; which ſuppoſes they were made into a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Form before.</q> Now what doth the Doctor think might be noted here (according to his way of making notes) upon <hi>precem facimus?</hi> But for my part I think the Ancients, by making Prayers, and by uſing Prayers, meant much what the ſame thing, <hi>viz</hi> performing the duty of Prayer. Moreover, St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath this Expreſſion, <hi>Si petamus ipſius ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione;</hi> And this he immediately interprets (I think) by our governing our ſelves in this Duty by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections he had laid down about it. And his account of theſe Directions is very like that <hi>Tertullian</hi> had given of them before him:<note place="margin">Id.</note> 
                  <hi>Sit autem orantibus ſermo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:56330:27"/> &amp; precatio cum diſciplina, quietem continens, &amp; pudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> There are two Paſſages more relating to this matter, which the Doctor quotes out of this Author, in which he conſiders the words the Author uſeth, but neglects the ſenſe and meaning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor had, in his uſing of thoſe words. The firſt is this, <hi>Publica eſt nobis &amp; communis oratio.</hi> Now St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>'s meaning is neither more nor leſs than this; That Chriſtians muſt not be ſo confined and narrow-ſpirited, in their Prayers, as to pray only for themſelves, but they muſt extend their Prayers to others, and pray for all People. He does not call the Chriſtians Prayer <hi>publick and common,</hi> becauſe he ſpeaks of the Lord's Prayer, as the Doctor pretends, nor as intimating that there was one fixed preſcribed form, which all were to uſe, but becauſe their prayers were not to be confined to themſelves, but to be general or univerſal extending to all Men. That this is the plain and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious ſenſe of this place, I appeal to any one, who will conſider what goes a little before, and what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately follows theſe words, <hi>Ante omnia pacis doctor, atque unitatis magiſter ſingulatim noluit &amp; privatim precem fieri, ut quis cum precatur, pro ſe tantum pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetur — publica eſt nobis, &amp; communis oratio, &amp; quum oramus, non pro uno, ſed pro populo toto oramus.</hi> This is alſo the plain meaning of his next Quotation, as you will eaſily perceive when you ſee the ſentence entire which is thus;<note place="margin">Cypr. Ep. ad Cler. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nuſquiſque oret dominum non pro ſe tantùm, ſed &amp; pro omnibus fratribus, ſicut Dominus Jeſus orare nos docuit, ubi non ſingulis privatam precem mandavit, ſed communi &amp; concordi prece orare pro om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus juſſit.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:56330:27"/>
               <p>The Doctor ſaith there are ſtill more evident Proofs in this Author, not only of Forms,<note place="margin">P. 66.</note> but of a Liturgy. And his firſt Inſtance is out of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Sermon concerning the Lord's Prayer. I forbear a great many Reflections I might eaſily make on what the Doctor ſaith concerning this Paſſage; I will only mind you, that a <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in the preſent ſenſe of that Phraſe, muſt be proved to be in St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s time, before it can be owned that he cited <hi>Surſum Corda,</hi> out of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer. And notwithſtanding this Phraſe is to be found in Liturgies framed long after St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>'s time, it doth not appear there was any ſuch Liturgy then; nor does St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſay a word here of this Phraſe being uſed in the Euchariſt, though Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies ſince framed, have inſerted it in that Office. Now the whole St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith about this matter amounts but to this; He having exhorted the People to keep their minds and hearts very intent upon what ſhould be their buſineſs when they are offering up their Prayers unto God; he explains to them the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of an Exhortation the Prieſt did uſually give them, before he began his prayer.<note place="margin">Cypr. de Orat. Dom.</note> 
                  <hi>Ideo &amp; ſacerdos ante orationem praefatione praemiſſa, parat fratrum mentes dicendo, Surſum corda, ut dum reſpondet plebs, Habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ad Dominum, admoneatur nihil aliud ſe quàm Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum cogitare debere.</hi> And from hence he inforces on them his former Inſtruction or Exhortation. Now if a Miniſter cannot pray but in a preſcribed Form, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that he hath deſired the People to lift up their hearts to God, and they have declared their readineſs to concur with him therein, this may paſs for a proof of preſcribed Liturgies. The preſent buſineſs
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:56330:28"/> is not to enquire what inferences others have made from this Paſſage, but whether a preſcribed Liturgy be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceable from a Miniſters deſiring the People before he begins to pray, to lift up their hearts to God, and attend to what ſhould be the main buſineſs of Prayer, or from their anſwering that they are ready and willing to concur with him in what he deſires of them?</p>
               <p>Here appearing ſo little evidence for Liturgies in this Paſſage, I proceed to the Doctor's next more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent proof for a Liturgy out of this Author.<note place="margin">P. 67.</note> 
                  <q rend="inline">We may obſerve (ſaith the Doctor) not only by this Preface, but alſo by another Paſſage that the <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> Church and the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> did hugely agree in theſe Liturgick Forms, becauſe, as the <hi>Greeks</hi> ſay, <hi>Give holy things to thoſe that are Holy.</hi> So it ſeems they did at <hi>Carthage,</hi> where (as St <hi>Cyprian</hi> notes) they were daily charged to keep that which was Holy in a pure Conſcience, according to our Lord's Command, not to caſt that which is Holy to Dogs, that is, in the Euchariſt (which they then daily cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated) they uſed that Phraſe, Give Holy things to Holy Perſons.</q> Now the truth, with reference to this paſſage, is this; St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> in the beginning of his Diſcourſe againſt <hi>Demetrian,</hi> acquaints him why he had ſo long choſen rather to keep ſilence, than to make a formal anſwer to his Calumnies and Railery; And for his warrant in doing thus, he quotes ſome places of Scripture, and immediately inſerts theſe words;<note place="margin">Cypr. ad Demet.</note> 
                  <hi>Et Sanctum quoque jubeamur intra cenſcientiam noſtram tenere, nec conculcandum porcis &amp; canibus ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponere:</hi> For the proof of which command or charge, he refers, not to their Communion Service, or their
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:56330:28"/> Office at the Euchariſt, (as the Doctor hints) but to a Paſſage of our Saviour's, as it is laid down expreſly in the Goſpel: <hi>Loquente Domino, &amp; dicente, ne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deritis ſanctum canibus, neque miſeritis margaritas veſtras ante porcos, &amp;c.</hi> In this ſame Tract the Doctor pretends to find a Chriſtian Litany;<note place="margin">P. 68.</note> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to the ſame page he had quoted for the former Paſſage, but you will find the Paſſage he ſpeaks of, towards the latter end of this Tract. Here St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, That notwithſtanding Chriſtians can rejoyce in every Condition, and patiently bear the moſt adverſe occurrences, becauſe of the reſpect they have unto the happy and bleſſed Eſtate which is to come; yet they do as occaſion requires offer up their Prayers to God for temporal bleſſings, and the removing or moderating of Adverſities, <hi>&amp;c. Et tamen pro arcendis hoſtibus, &amp; imbribus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trandis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cypr. Cont. Demet.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; vel auferendis vel temperandis adverſis rogamus ſemper, &amp; preces fundimus, &amp;c.</hi> Now becauſe St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> do give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome things which were the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Chriſtians conſtant or occaſional Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, (for I ſuppoſe the Doctor doth hardly think the Chriſtians did every day pray for the procuring of Rain) therefore the Doctor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes they had a Liturgy; And becauſe the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars mentioned, were prayed for in the Ancient Litanies, (though much younger than either of theſe two Authors) therefore in the times of theſe Authors, they had a certain Form, though they concealed the phraſes of it from unbelievers. If any Man can ſee any ſtrength in this way of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guing, before it be proved that theſe things cannot
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:56330:29"/> be prayed for but in preſcribed words, I muſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge he can ſee farther than I can.</p>
               <p>The Doctor having produced theſe Teſtimonies from St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 69.</note> to evidence a Liturgy in his days, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies himſelf to anſwer ſome Paſſages Mr. <hi>Clarkson</hi> had offered from this Author, to prove that in his days, thoſe who did officiate were at liberty to expreſs themſelves in their Prayers as they thought moſt convenient. The firſt Quotation for this purpoſe is out of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> where he gives him an account of their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God for him ſuitably to the preſent occaſion which was offered them. This occaſion of offering up their prayers for him was particular, and ſuch as was not incident every day. The Queſtion now is this, Whether ſeeing they did pray for him with a particular regard to what is related in that Epiſtle, the Petitions they offered up were preſcribed, or whether they were expreſt freely according as the occaſion required? I ſhall leave the indifferent Reader, when he peruſeth what the Doctor hath ſaid about this matter, to conclude as he ſhall ſee fit, whether the Doctor hath cleared this Paſſage to his ſatisfaction. For I think the Queſtion is not, whether thoſe words he relates there, were the very words they conſtantly uſed on that occaſion; but whether there was a Prayer ready preſcribed for that occaſion? If there were not, and they did ordinarily pray for the things mentioned without being confined to uſe the ſame words every time, do you judge whether this Paſſage do make more for the Doctor or Mr. <hi>Clarkſon.</hi> It is in my judgment, but a poor anſwer for the Doctor to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:56330:29"/> inſinuate,<note place="margin">P. 70.</note> that a Primate may occaſionally pray without a preſcribed Form, but inferiour Prieſts may not, unleſs Miniſterial abilities are not to be exerciſed proportionably to the meaſure in which God hath conferred the ſame, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly as thoſe who have them can climb up towards the top of Eccleſiaſtical Dignity and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">His ſecond Allegation (ſaith the Doctor) out of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> for ſuch occaſional Prayers is,<note place="margin">P. 71.</note> that there are alſo mention of ſuch occaſional Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Epiſtle to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Maximus;</hi> but he durſt not (ſaith the Doctor) cite the place at large, which only ſpeaks of private Prayers made by theſe Confeſſors in priſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </q> Now becauſe the Doctor hath ſuch a mind to have the place cited at large, I will do it, and then leave you to judge whether it only ſpeaks of private Prayers, or whether the Paſſage do ſpeak at all of the Prayers of theſe Confeſſors? Mr. <hi>Clark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> refers to the particular Epiſtle, and the words are theſe, <hi>Et nos quidem veſtri, diebus ac noctibus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr.</hi> epiſt. ad <hi>Moſ.</hi> &amp; <hi>Maxim.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>me mores, &amp; quando in ſacrificiis precem cum pluribus facimus, &amp; cum in ſeceſſu privatis precibus oramus, coronis ac laudibus veſtris plenam domini faventiam poſtulamus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is one inſtance more,<note place="margin">P. 71.</note> the Doctor takes notice of, and ſeems to be in ſome paſſion with Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> about it. Now the matter ſtands thus; Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> in one part of his Book is ſhewing that the Ancients were not ſo wedded to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar words and phraſes, as ſome have been in lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter years. And to give ſome proof of this, he
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:56330:30"/> doth ſhew amongſt other inſtances, that they did not conceive Chriſt had ſo tied them up in the Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, that they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily uſe juſt thoſe very words he had ſet down relating to this matter in the Goſpel; but that they had leave to vary their expreſſions, and change thoſe words related in the Goſpel for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, provided they did not change the ſence. He ſhews they did ordinarily vary in ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, and amongſt the reſt he ſaith ſome thought themſelves not obliged to Baptiſe expreſly, in the name of the Sacred Trinity, ſo as to name every perſon, as they are mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. but in the name of Chriſt, or of the Lord Jeſus, or of the Lord. He farther adds, and this ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be the practice of the beſt times, hath great Advocates. He names ſeveral, who are, and were far enough from being lookt upon as Hereticks. Afterwards he quotes this very Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> which creates the Doctor ſo much diſturbance. The Doctor ſeems to be diſpleaſed becauſe Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> did not quote the Paſſage entire,<note place="margin">P. 72.</note> without leaving out any words; and then tells us St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> words are theſe: <q rend="inline">How then do ſome ſay, <hi>who are cut of the Church, yea againſt the Church,</hi> that if a Pagan be any where, or any way Baptiſed in the name of Chriſt Jeſus, he may obtain the Remiſſion of Sins?</q> And hereupon the Doctor falls into a warm ſort of ſhort talk about Hereticks and Schiſmaticks. Now St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> words are theſe; <hi>Quomodo ergo quidam dicunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cypr.</hi> ad. Jubai.</note> 
                  <hi>foris extra eccleſiam, modo in nomine Jeſu Chriſti ubicun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> &amp; quemodocun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:56330:30"/> gentilem Baptizatum Remiſſionem peccatorum conſequi poſſe?</hi> I will not diſpute whether the Doctor hath tranſlated this Paſſage as it ought to be tranſlated, though I do not know any neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that there is, that <hi>foris extra eccleſiam,</hi> muſt be uſed as explanatory of <hi>quidam.</hi> But all that Mr. <hi>Clarkſon</hi> brought this Paſſage for, was to prove that ſome in St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> days were of the above mentioned opinion And I think the quotation is full to that point. He did not produce this place to prove they were Orthodox in St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prians</hi> Judgement, but he doth expreſly declare St <hi>Cyprian</hi> did not allow it; yet I am not ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that it doth follow they were either Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks or Schiſmaticks, becauſe <hi>foris extra eccleſiam,</hi> is in this ſentence.</p>
               <p>The Doctors next proof for Liturgies is from the account St. <hi>Baſil</hi> gives concerning <hi>Gregory Thau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maturgus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 72.</note>
                  <q rend="inline">who was ſo much for a Liturgy that we have the teſtimony of St. <hi>Baſil</hi> (ſaith the Doctor) concerning him, that he appointed a Form of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er for that Church of <hi>Noeoceſarea,</hi>
                  </q> from which they would not vary in one Ceremony, or in a Word; nor would they add one myſtical Form to thoſe which he had left them. Now the Caſe was thus. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> was proving the Divinity of the Holy Spirit,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil.</hi> de Spir. ſancto. <hi>cap. 29.</hi>
                  </note> from the Ancients <hi>Aſcribing Glory and Power to the Father, and the Son, with the Holy Spirit.</hi> And having named ſeveral of the Ancients who had taught that Glory and Power were to be Aſcribed to the Spirit, as well as to the Father, and the Son, he at laſt mentions <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the Great, and proves that he was of the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:56330:31"/> ſame mind, from the preſent practice of that Church. And to make it appear they had not varied from the Doctrine of that great man, he reports the profound reſpect the people of that Country ſtill had for him.<note place="margin">P. 73.</note> So that [<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the Doctor relates in his Margin] they would not add any Practice, any Word, or any myſtical Form in the Church to what he had left with them. By which I conceive he means, that they did ſtrictly obſerve that way and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod for their ordinary Worſhip, and kept ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to thoſe Doctrines, and that way of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacrament which were in uſe in <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi> time. <hi>But he doth not ſay one word of</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie's <hi>appointing a Form of Prayer for that Church.</hi> Nor does it follow that becauſe they Worſhiped God in the ſame manner, a great many years after <hi>Gregory,</hi> wherein they worſhipped him in his time, that therefore they uſed the very words he uſed. Whereas, it is ſaid they did not add a word to what he left with them, that doth not relate to their Prayers, but to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine he taught; for here St. <hi>Baſil</hi> is ſpeaking of the Divinity of the Holy Spirit, and proving that Doctrine. And in other places St. <hi>Baſil</hi> takes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice how tenacious they were of the Words in which <hi>Gregory</hi> did deliver the Doctrines of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity unto them, particularly to prove his own Doctrine to be the ſame with what <hi>Gregory</hi> did teach,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 75.</note> he alledged his having learned from <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rina</hi> the Doctrines of Faith in the very words wherein <hi>Gregory</hi> had delivered them. If it ſhall be ſaid he is here proving the Divinity of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:56330:31"/> Holy Spirit by a part of their Worſhip, <hi>viz.</hi> their aſcribing Glory and Power to God, what can be inferred from thence is but this; That <hi>Gregory</hi> had taught them when they did aſcribe, Glory and Power to the Father and Son, to add alſo, <hi>With the Holy Spirit.</hi> St. <hi>Baſil</hi> farther adds, They were ſo tenacious of what <hi>Gregory</hi> had taught and practiſed amongſt them, they would not depart from that ſimplicity in the Celebrating of the Worſhip of God, which he obſerved, though a more Pompous and Ceremonious way did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail in other Churches, and which ſome thought did better ſuit with the alteration of their cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances. But here you may take notice that St. <hi>Baſil</hi> doth not alledge any Liturgy, <hi>Gregory</hi> had compoſed for them, but only pleads the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent uſage of that Church, and argues it was the ſame in <hi>Gregories</hi> days, not becauſe they had a Liturgy of his Compoſing, but becauſe their reſpect to him all along to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time was ſuch, they would not ſuffer any addition to be made, to the method or order he obſerved, or to the Doctrines he had taught. To me it appears plain, that there was not any Liturgy of <hi>Gregories</hi> Compoſing, St. <hi>Baſil</hi> could produce for his preſent purpoſe; but finding ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the uſe of that Church which was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to his buſineſs, he alledges that, and the better to inforce that allegation, he urges the great probability there was that they received it from him; and to put the more colour upon this, he breaks forth into a Rhetorical <hi>Encomium</hi> on that Father, and the great reſpect the people of that
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:56330:32"/> Country had for him. So that the ſentence the Doctor quotes, only entertains us with an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbolical account of the reſpect the people had for <hi>Gregory.</hi> For St, <hi>Baſil</hi> himſelf doth ſpeak much otherwiſe of this matter when it comes in his way upon a diſſerent occaſion. And par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in that very Epiſtle the Doctor refers us to, in the next place, for a proof <q rend="inline">that this <hi>Gregory</hi> had appointed that Church a particular way of ſinging the Pſalms,<note place="margin">P. 73.</note> of which the <hi>Noeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſarean</hi> Clergy were ſo extreamly tenacious, that when St. <hi>Baſil</hi> would have brought in a better way, they oppoſed him in it, and objected that it was not ſo in the days of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great.</q> 'Tis true, it was objected againſt that way of ſinging St. <hi>Baſil</hi> would have introduced, that it was not in uſe there, in the time of <hi>Gregory,</hi> But if you conſider the Anſwer St. <hi>Baſil</hi> makes to this Objection, you will find him giving an account of the <hi>Noeoceſareans</hi> very different from that we have in his Book <hi>de Spiritu Sancto.</hi> Amongſt other things which he ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil</hi> Epiſt. <hi>63.</hi> ad Cler. <hi>Noeoceſ.</hi>
                  </note> he peremptorily enquires <hi>By what Teſtimonies will they make it evident, that thoſe things; which he recommends to them, were not in uſe in the time of</hi> Gregory? Now aſſuredly this was a very ſtrange ſort of queſtion, if he knew they had a <hi>Liturgy</hi> of <hi>Gregory</hi>'s Compoſing, which they conſtantly made uſe of. Or if they had but an <hi>Order</hi> of his framing, which they were ſtrictly to obſerve in the ſeveral parts of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Yea, he tells them to whom he Writes, that they had not preſerved any of thoſe inſtances then uſed pure and uncorrupt unto that time.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:56330:32"/> moreover he very plainly intimates, that there was no way to make a true judgment of what <hi>Gregory</hi> did, but by conſulting the Holy Scriptures. When he mentions ſeveral particulars, which he affirms concerning <hi>Gregory,</hi> he doth not quote his Liturgy, his Rubrick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but expreſs words of Scripture: particularly he ſaith, That <hi>Gregory Prayed with his Head uncovered.</hi> Now how doth he prove this? Not from any order <hi>Gregory</hi> had made concerning this matter, but becauſe the Apoſtle had ſaid, <hi>Every man Praying or Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cying, with his Head covered, diſhonoureth his Head;</hi> And <hi>Gregory</hi> (ſaith he) was <hi>a genuine Diſciple of the Apoſtles.</hi> Thus you have an account of thoſe two Paſſages the Doctor doth quote out of St. <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil.</hi> And you may now judge whether <hi>it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to have a clearer proof in the World for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Forms than this;</hi> And whether the Doctor had any occaſion given him from theſe Allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to break forth into ſuch a Vaunting Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as he entertains his Reader with, upon his having produced theſe quotations?</p>
               <p>As for what the Doctor quotes out of <hi>Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> concerning <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus;</hi> It only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Hymns; and I am not ſenſible that the way of arguing is cogent, That becauſe people do ſing Hymns compoſed to their hands, therefore they do or muſt neceſſarily pray by preſcribed Forms. One might think the <hi>Precentor of York</hi> ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the difference there is, betwixt praying, and ſinging, if any knowledge of the nature, and uſe of ſinging, of framing the voice into a regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, melodious, tunable ſound, in order to the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:56330:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> raiſing of the affections, be at all neceſſary to that <hi>Character.</hi> And a due conſideration of that, might have prevented a great many tautologies which are to be found in his Scholaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and would have made his Diſcourſe much ſhorter than it is, though it muſt have deprived the Reader of many of thoſe flights (which it may be) the Doctor conceits are very graceful. But if you have a mind to peruſe the Paſſage (the Doctor ſpeaks of) in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult <hi>Valeſius</hi> his Edition, you muſt not look for it where the Doctor's Margin directs, but in <hi>lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="inline">I ſhall add no more (ſaith the Doctor) in this <hi>Century,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">P. 76.</note> but to obſerve, that in the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> recorded by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius,</hi> it appears to have been the general uſage of the Church, for every one of the People to Say <hi>Amen,</hi> when they heard the Prieſt offer them the Sacrament,<note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>35.</hi> p. <hi>180.</hi>
                     </note> and ſay, The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which was a Form ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally uſed in all Churches of the world, that we may conclude it was enjoyned by all Liturgies.</q> What Edition of <hi>Euſebius</hi> the Doctor made uſe of, I do not know. But his Margin gives me no aſſiſtance for the finding of the place he ſpeaks of. The <hi>Form,</hi> the Doctor ſaith, was ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally uſed, I ſuppoſe is theſe words, <hi>The Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. Now I do not remember that <hi>Euſebius</hi> doth any where in his Sixth Book report, either from <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> or any other, that thoſe words were univerſally uſed on the occaſion the Doctor mentions. But there is
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:56330:33"/> a paſſage in his Sixth Book which hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of what the Doctor mentions; whether that be the place the Doctor means, I know not. I will give you the Engliſh of it, and refer you to the Author, to ſee whether you can find any thing there for the Doctor's purpoſe.<note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>43</hi> p. <hi>245.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> ſaith that <hi>Cornelius</hi> relates to <hi>Fabius</hi> the worſt of all the wickedneſſes which <hi>Novatus</hi> was guil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty of, which was this. <hi>When he hath conſecrated the Elements, dividing unto every one a Portion, and giving it unto him, he compels thoſe wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons to ſwear inſtead of giving thanks, for catching the hands of him who receiveth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in both his hands, he doth not looſe them till he hath ſworn in this manner (for I will report his words) Swear to me by the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that thou wilt never for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake me, and turn to</hi> Cornelius. <hi>And the miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man doth not taſte of the Elements, till he hath firſt pronounced a Curſe upon himſelf; and when he receives that Bread, inſtead of ſaying,</hi> Amen, <hi>He ſaith I will not return to</hi> Cornelius. If this be the paſſage the Doctor means, here is nothing ſaid of the peoples hearing the Prieſt ſay theſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular words, <hi>The Body of our Lord Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c. Beſides, this paſſage is not in <hi>Dionyſius</hi> his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, but in <hi>Cornelius</hi> his Epiſtle to <hi>Fabius.</hi> But yet there is in <hi>Euſebius</hi>'s Seventh Book an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> which hath ſomething in it that hath ſome reſemblance to ſome part of that the Doctor relates; I will give you an account of that, and then I have done with the Doctors quotations for this <hi>Century. Dionyſius</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:56330:34"/> to <hi>Xyſtus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>9.</hi> p. <hi>255.</hi>
                  </note> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> relates how one who had been eſteemed, or reckoned a great while for one of the Faithful, upon his obſerving how Baptiſm was celebrated amongſt the Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox, was in very great trouble, becauſe having been Baptiſed amongſt the Hereticks, his Baptiſm was not the ſame, nor had not any thing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon with the Baptiſm of the Orthodox; And therefore he was very deſirous to be Baptiſed again. <hi>Dionyſius</hi> durſt not do it, but told him, that his long continued Communion with the Church was ſufficient. <hi>For I may not Baptiſe him again, who hath often heard the Praiſes which are offered unto God, and hath anſwered with the reſt,</hi> Amen; <hi>who hath ſtood at the Table, and hath ſtretched forth his hands to take the Sacred Food, and hath received the ſame, and hath for a conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent time been partaker of the Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> If this be the paſſage the Doctor means, you will eaſily perceive, that he gives not a fair account of it, and that it is not at all for his purpoſe. I do not ſee how a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Liturgy can be inferred from either of theſe paſſages related out of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> no nor (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing good evidence that the Prieſt did conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe theſe words, <hi>The Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. in diſtributing and giving the Bread unto the people) how we can juſtly conclude there was a preſcribed Liturgy, from the words of which, the Prieſt muſt never vary in any of his Prayers and Praiſes in Publick?</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:56330:34"/>
               <p>Sir, I think I have now given you a true account of all thoſe paſſages the Doctor hath produced out of the Ancients, for Liturgies, in the three Firſt <hi>Centuries.</hi> It is eaſie for any man, who lays aſide prejudice, and will form a judgment of matters only in proportion to the evidence which is offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them, to determine whether His Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be a ſolid proof of that for which he produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth them.</p>
               <p>I have conſined my ſelf to what the Doctor alledgeth for Liturgies in the three Firſt <hi>Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> becauſe I think this pretended Antiquity of Liturgies is deſigned, not to juſtifie their <hi>lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (and would we content our ſelves with that, and effectually prove their expediency, the breach betwixt us, and the greateſt part of our Fellow-Proteſtants relating to this matter, would ſoon be made up) but to introduce, or ſupport an Opinion of their <hi>Neceſſity</hi> in the <hi>Chriſtian Church.</hi> And I conceive the three Firſt <hi>Centuries,</hi> is a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od of ſufficient extent for an enquiry, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a matter ſo circumſtanced. The <hi>lawfulneſs</hi> of Liturgies may be argued from more Rational Topicks, than Humane Authority. Their <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diency</hi> muſt be judged of, upon a juſt weighing of circumſtances; Their <hi>Neceſſity</hi> cannot be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by any Topick.</p>
               <p>Thoſe who attempt to advance the Neceſſity of Liturgies, do not only oppoſe them, who were wont to be called Diſſenters, but are appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently managing a Deſign againſt the moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Judicious, and Moderate, who are in the Communion of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:56330:35"/> it may be proper enough, for one of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to mind ſuch Perſons, That to catch up ſome words and Phraſes, which are to be found in the Writings of the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Chriſtian Church, leaving their ſenſe behind, and then tacking them together in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes about Liturgies, will no more prove Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies to be as Ancient as they pretend, than the Artificial Faſtning of a <hi>Long Gray-Beard</hi> to a Youth's <hi>Chin,</hi> will prove him to be a very Old Man.</p>
               <p>Sir, With reference to the following Part of the Doctor's Book, I ſhall only tell you at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, That I take it to be of a <hi>Piece</hi> with that Part I have already conſidered. And if you are deſirous to have a more diſtinct account of the Greateſt Part of his more Numerous Quotations in the Fourth <hi>Century,</hi> you need not give your ſelf any further trouble, than to ſignifie your pleaſure to</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your Moſt Affectionate Friend, and Faithful Servant,</hi> &amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:56330:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
